<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" ?><transcript><text start="9.92" dur="7.6">Good to see all of you.You see a quote up
there by Niels Bohr, one of the founding figures</text><text start="17.52" dur="4.21">of quantum mechanics: “Anyone who thinks
they can talk about quantum mechanics without</text><text start="21.73" dur="3.93">getting dizzy hasn’t yet understood the
first word of it.”</text><text start="25.66" dur="1.93">Now, why would that be?</text><text start="27.59" dur="2.59">What did Niels Bohr mean by that?</text><text start="30.18" dur="5.81">Well, basically he meant that we all have
a good intuition for classical physics.</text><text start="35.99" dur="1">Right?</text><text start="36.99" dur="2.63">And by that, I mean, you know, if I was to
take any little object, right, and give it</text><text start="39.62" dur="1.71">a catch.</text><text start="41.33" dur="1">Nice!</text><text start="42.33" dur="2.45">Did a one-handed catch right there.</text><text start="44.78" dur="1.27">Throw this a little bit further back.</text><text start="46.05" dur="1.49">Here we go, two for two.</text><text start="47.54" dur="1.3">Nope, we’re still one-for-two.</text><text start="48.84" dur="3.22">They’re still back in the dark ages--here
we go.</text><text start="52.06" dur="1.56">You have that one over there?</text><text start="53.62" dur="1">Good.</text><text start="54.62" dur="4.619">Right now, each one of the people who caught,
so that would be the two of you over here,</text><text start="59.239" dur="2.261">is really an evolved human being.</text><text start="61.5" dur="9.23">Now, you see, when we were out there in the
savannah trying to survive, we needed certain</text><text start="70.73" dur="5.28">skills, we needed to be able to know where
to throw a spear or how to throw a rock to</text><text start="76.01" dur="1.01">get the next meal.</text><text start="77.02" dur="4.419">We needed to dodge some animal that was running
toward us.</text><text start="81.44" dur="7.68">And therefore we learned the basic physics
of the everyday macroscopic so-called classical world.</text><text start="89.16" dur="1.94">We learned that intuitively.</text><text start="91.11" dur="5.58">And that’s why when I throw an object, you
don’t have to through some elaborate calculation</text><text start="96.69" dur="2.819">to figure out the trajectory of that stuffed
animal.</text><text start="99.509" dur="1.92">You just put out your hand and catch it.</text><text start="101.429" dur="3.411">It’s built into our being.</text><text start="104.84" dur="4.959">But that’s not the case when we go beyond
the world of the everyday.</text><text start="109.8" dur="3.629">If we explore the world, say of the very small, which is what we are going to focus on here tonight,</text><text start="113.429" dur="3.451">we don’t have experience in that
domain.</text><text start="116.88" dur="1.919">We don’t have intuition in that domain.</text><text start="118.799" dur="6.551">And in fact, were it the case that any of
our distant brethren way in the past, if they</text><text start="125.35" dur="6.4">did have some quantum mechanical knowledge
and they sat down to think about electrons</text><text start="131.75" dur="6.36">and probability waves and wave functions and
things of that sort, they got eaten!</text><text start="138.11" dur="3.23">Their genes didn’t propagate, right?</text><text start="141.34" dur="6.38">And therefore we have to use the power of
mathematics and experiment and observation</text><text start="147.72" dur="9.14">to peer deeper into the true nature of reality
when things are beyond our direct sensory experience.</text><text start="157.28" dur="3.46">And that’s what quantum mechanics is all
about.</text><text start="160.75" dur="6.239">It’s trying to describe what happens in
the micro-world in a way that is both accurate</text><text start="166.989" dur="1.341">and revealing.</text><text start="168.33" dur="4.04">And the thing to bear in mind is that even
though our focus here tonight will really</text><text start="172.37" dur="6.43">in some sense be in the microworld, the world
of particles, we are all a collection of particles.</text><text start="178.8" dur="5.59">So any weirdness that we find down there in
the microworld, in some sense it has an impact</text><text start="184.39" dur="4.75">even in the macroworld and maybe suppresses--we’ll
discuss.</text><text start="189.14" dur="3.16">But it’s not like there’s a sharp divide
between the small and the big.</text><text start="192.3" dur="2.469">We are big beings made of a lot of small things.</text><text start="194.769" dur="5.53">So any weirdness about the small stuff really
does apply to us as well.</text><text start="200.299" dur="4.64">And in this journey into the micro-world,
the world of quantum mechanics, we have some</text><text start="204.939" dur="3.741">of the world leading experts to help us along,
to figure things out.</text><text start="208.68" dur="3.51">And let me now bring them on stage.</text><text start="212.19" dur="5.76">Joining us tonight is a professor of philosophy
at the University of Southern California who</text><text start="217.95" dur="5.8">spent 22 years at the University of Oxford
as a student, researcher, and faculty member.</text><text start="223.75" dur="4">He is the author of a book on the Everett
interpretation of quantum mechanics titled</text><text start="227.75" dur="1.42">&amp;quot;The Emergent Multiverse.&amp;quot;</text><text start="229.17" dur="4.93">Please welcome David Wallace.</text><text start="234.1" dur="4.469">Also joining us tonight is a professor of
chemistry at the University of California,</text><text start="238.569" dur="4.861">Berkeley, co-director of the Berkeley Quantum
Information and Computation Center and faculty</text><text start="243.43" dur="2.699">scientist at the Lawrence Berkeley National
Laboratory.</text><text start="246.129" dur="5.211">She’s a fellow of the American Physical
Society and recipient of awards from the Bergmann, Sloan,</text><text start="251.34" dur="2.46">Alexander von Humboldt Foundations.</text><text start="253.8" dur="2.76">Please welcome K. Birgitta Whaley.</text><text start="260.4" dur="6.06">Our third participant is a professor of physics
at the Univeristy of British Columbia, a Simons</text><text start="266.6" dur="4.56">Investigator and member of the Simons Foundation
“It from Qubit” collaboration.</text><text start="271.17" dur="6.47">He was a Canada research chair and Sloan Foundation
fellow and was awarded the Canadian CAP medal</text><text start="277.64" dur="2.87">for mathematical physics for 2014.</text><text start="280.51" dur="3.79">Please welcome Mark Van Raamsdonk.</text><text start="286.54" dur="6.46">Our final participant is a professor of theoretical
physics at Utrecht University in the Netherlands</text><text start="293.01" dur="6.31">and winner of the 1999 Nobel Prize in Physics
for work in quantum field theory that laid</text><text start="299.32" dur="4.66">the foundations for the standard model of
particle physics, one of the greatest minds</text><text start="303.98" dur="6.3">of our era, please welcome Gerard ‘t Hooft.</text><text start="315.92" dur="7.32">Alright, so the subject is quantum mechanics,
and part of the evening will involve</text><text start="323.4" dur="4.76">some challenge to the conventional thinking about quantum mechanics.</text><text start="328.17" dur="4.61">And so before we get into the details, I thought
I would just sort of take your temperature.</text><text start="332.78" dur="2.77">Get a sense of where you stand on quantum
mechanics.</text><text start="335.55" dur="1.98">Is it, in your mind, a done deal?</text><text start="337.53" dur="2.29">It’s finished, we completely understand
it?</text><text start="339.82" dur="1.42">Is it a provisional theory?</text><text start="341.24" dur="4.62">Is it something which 100 years from now we’re
gonna look back on with a quaint smile?</text><text start="345.86" dur="2.67">“How did they think that that’s how things
worked?”</text><text start="348.53" dur="1.43">So, David, your view.</text><text start="349.96" dur="2.66">Well I don’t think we fully understand it
yet.</text><text start="352.62" dur="4.28">I think it has a lot of depth left to plumb,
and who knows it might turn out to be replaced.</text><text start="356.9" dur="4.32">But right at the minute, I think we don’t
have either empirical or theoretical reason</text><text start="361.22" dur="1.86">to think that anything will take its place.</text><text start="363.2" dur="0.9">Good</text><text start="364.66" dur="2">I think it’s here to stay.</text><text start="367.02" dur="5.84">There maybe extensions, modifications, there
may be something more complete, but this will</text><text start="372.86" dur="2.28">still be part of it, in my view.</text><text start="375.14" dur="1">OK, Mark</text><text start="376.14" dur="4.17">Yeah, so there’s a frontier in quantum mechanics
that I work in, and this is the frontier.</text><text start="380.31" dur="5.07">It’s like the wild west of theoretical physics,
where we’re trying to combine quantum mechanics</text><text start="385.38" dur="4.27">and gravity, and we need to do that to understand
black holes and hopefully eventually understand</text><text start="389.65" dur="1.55">the big bang.</text><text start="391.2" dur="4.89">And there’s a lot to do, and we don’t
know if we’re going to have to modify quantum</text><text start="396.09" dur="3.95">mechanics, or it will all be the same quantum
mechanics all the way down.</text><text start="400.04" dur="3.62">Now, Gerard, you have unusual views.</text><text start="403.66" dur="5.24">Well yes, I could spend the rest of the evening
explaining them.</text><text start="408.9" dur="8.32">But, to my mind, quantum mechanics is a tool,
a very important mathematical tool, to calculate</text><text start="417.22" dur="3.69">what happens if you have some underlying equations.</text><text start="420.91" dur="6.09">And telling us how particles and other small
things behave.</text><text start="427" dur="2.77">We know the answer to that question--the answer
is quantum mechanics.</text><text start="429.77" dur="3.77">But we don’t know the question, that’s
still something we’re trying to figure out.</text><text start="433.54" dur="1">Good.</text><text start="434.54" dur="2.49">So, sort of a jeopardy issue, if you know
the American reference.</text><text start="437.03" dur="1">(Exactly.)</text><text start="438.03" dur="1.91">Alright, so just a quick overview.</text><text start="439.94" dur="4.09">We’re going to start with some of the basics
of quantum mechanics just to sort of make</text><text start="444.03" dur="2.65">sure that all of us are more or less on the
same page.</text><text start="446.68" dur="5.1">We’ll then turn to a section on something
called the “quantum measurement problem,”</text><text start="451.78" dur="3.2">something weird, “quantum entanglement”
as in the title of the program.</text><text start="454.98" dur="6">We’ll then turn to issues of black holes,
spacetime, and quantum computation, which</text><text start="460.98" dur="2.39">will take us right through to the end.</text><text start="463.37" dur="5.11">Alright, so just to get to the basics of quantum
mechanics.</text><text start="468.48" dur="5.55">The story, of course, began more or less in
the way that I started.</text><text start="474.03" dur="6.2">We understood the world using classical physics
in the early days, way back to the 1600s.</text><text start="480.23" dur="4.89">And then something happened in the early part
of the 20th century, where people like--we</text><text start="485.12" dur="7.36">started with Newton, of course, then we moved
on to people like Max Planck, Albert Einstein.</text><text start="492.48" dur="5.39">What drove the initial move into quantum physics?</text><text start="497.87" dur="1.62">David?</text><text start="499.49" dur="4.6">I think it was really just pushing really
hard at classical mechanics as it went down</text><text start="504.09" dur="4.65">into the scale of atoms and the structure
of atoms, and just finding that that structure</text><text start="508.74" dur="1.85">snapped and broke.</text><text start="510.59" dur="6.28">That trying to use classical mechanics to
understand how hot things got or how electrons</text><text start="516.87" dur="2.89">went around atoms without collapsing into
the nucleus.</text><text start="519.76" dur="7.68">In all those places, we had a series of hints
that something was amiss in our classical physics.</text><text start="528.24" dur="6.82">And it took, I guess, most of 30 years for
those hints to coalesce into a coherent theory.</text><text start="535.06" dur="5.85">But that coherent theory then became not really
just a single physical theory, but the language</text><text start="540.91" dur="6.21">for writing physical theory, be it theories
of particles or fields, maybe someday even gravity.</text><text start="547.64" dur="3.759">And that language was more or less sort of
solid by, I guess about 1930.</text><text start="551.399" dur="1">Yup.</text><text start="552.399" dur="4.341">Yeah and it’s actually quite remarkable
that it only took that number of years to</text><text start="556.74" dur="2.96">develop a radically new way of thinking about
things.</text><text start="559.7" dur="6.26">And Richard Feynman, who is of course a hero
of all of us, also known to the public, famously</text><text start="565.96" dur="3.939">said that there was one experiment--we can
go through the whole history of everything</text><text start="569.899" dur="4.651">you described, with the ultraviolet catastrophe
and photoelectric effect and all these beautiful</text><text start="574.55" dur="6.51">experiments--but the Double Slit Experiment,
luckily for us, in having a relatively brief</text><text start="581.06" dur="6.11">conversation, allows us to get to the heart
of this new idea, where it came from.</text><text start="587.17" dur="4.1">This actually is the paper on, in some sense,
the Double Slit Experiment.</text><text start="591.27" dur="1.97">The first version, Davisson and Germer.</text><text start="593.24" dur="1.899">And I’ll draw your attention to one thing.</text><text start="595.139" dur="1.841">You see the word “accident”?</text><text start="596.98" dur="2.12">And this is just a footnote.</text><text start="599.1" dur="5.52">But, in the old days, people would actually
describe the blind alleys that they went down</text><text start="604.62" dur="1.75">in a scientific paper.</text><text start="606.37" dur="4.29">But as science progressed, we were kind of
taught, “no no don’t ever say what went wrong.</text><text start="611.08" dur="1.439">Only talk about what went right!”</text><text start="612.519" dur="4.531">But here is an old paper, and indeed this
experiment emerged from an accident in the</text><text start="617.05" dur="1.789">laboratory at Bell Labs.</text><text start="618.839" dur="3.961">They were doing a version of this experiment,
they turned the intensity up too high, some</text><text start="622.8" dur="5.74">glass tube shattered, and when they re-did
the experiment, unwittingly, they had changed</text><text start="628.54" dur="3.859">the experiment to something that was actually
far more interesting than the experiment they</text><text start="632.399" dur="2.081">were initially carrying out.</text><text start="634.48" dur="6.57">So, just to talk about what this experiment
is in modern language, so David again, just,</text><text start="641.05" dur="4.159">what’s the basic idea of the Double Slit
Experiment?</text><text start="645.209" dur="4.25">So you take a source of, well of particles
of any kind, but let it be light, for instance.</text><text start="649.459" dur="5.281">You shine that light as a narrow beam on a
screen--it has two gaps in it, and you look</text><text start="654.74" dur="5.55">at the pattern of light behind the two gaps
in the screen (“two slits”) two slits,</text><text start="660.29" dur="1">exactly, yes.</text><text start="661.29" dur="4.45">So the slits are just literally gaps in a
black sheet of paper, in principle.</text><text start="665.74" dur="2.11">The light’s going through.</text><text start="667.85" dur="6.64">If light is a particle, you’d expect one
sort of result on the far side of the screen.</text><text start="674.49" dur="3.3">If light is a wave, you might expect something
different as the light coming through one</text><text start="677.79" dur="4.31">part of the slit interferes with the light
going through the other part of the slit.</text><text start="682.1" dur="3.729">And the weird thing about the quantum two-slit
experiment is that it seems, in various ways,</text><text start="685.829" dur="1.94">to be doing both of those things at the same
time.</text><text start="687.769" dur="1">Good.</text><text start="688.769" dur="6.601">So, Birgitta, if you can just take us through
a particle experiment to build up our intuition.</text><text start="695.37" dur="3.71">So let’s say we carry out the experiment
the way we described, but we don’t start</text><text start="699.08" dur="3.819">with photons or electrons, we start with pellets--bullets
or something.</text><text start="702.899" dur="3.451">So I think we have a little animation that
you could take us through.</text><text start="706.35" dur="2.52">So what would we expect to happen in this
experiment?</text><text start="708.87" dur="5.75">Well so you have the source of the pellets
here in front of us, spitting out the pellets</text><text start="714.62" dur="3.159">and some of them go through the holes, and
the ones that go through the holes basically</text><text start="717.779" dur="4.941">travel rectilinear, straight ahead, as we
might expect from our classical intuition.</text><text start="722.72" dur="6.349">And we get two bands at the back, indicating
the pellets that went through the right slit,</text><text start="729.069" dur="4.101">on the right, and the left band is the pellets
that went through the left slit.</text><text start="733.17" dur="2.279">Now, if I was--that’s completely intuitive
right?</text><text start="735.449" dur="4.361">So this is the stuff that our forebears would
have known even on the savannah.</text><text start="739.81" dur="6.439">Now, if we took the size of the pellets and
we dialed them down to a very small size,</text><text start="746.249" dur="4.4">before going to your quantum intuition that
you have, what would you expect naively to</text><text start="750.649" dur="2.471">happen if you simply dialed down the size?</text><text start="753.12" dur="4.9">Would you expect there to be any different
if you were--this is a leading question, by the way.</text><text start="758.8" dur="1.659">So, just follow me here.</text><text start="760.459" dur="1.641">The answer is…would you expect anything
different?</text><text start="762.1" dur="1.289">Would you expect anything different?</text><text start="763.389" dur="2.551">(...obviously the same thing. No no not at all.)</text><text start="766.18" dur="1">Good.</text><text start="767.28" dur="1">Good.</text><text start="768.74" dur="1">Naively not!</text><text start="770.28" dur="1.94">Naively not. Exactly right.</text><text start="772.36" dur="2.56">So here’s what you would naively expect
would happen.</text><text start="774.93" dur="4.129">Again, you got the particles going through
the two slits.</text><text start="779.059" dur="6.591">So Mark, tell us what exactly does happen--not
that I don’t think Birgitta could, just</text><text start="785.65" dur="2.619">to give us all a little airtime.</text><text start="788.269" dur="4.711">So it’s of course, while the place where
you would least expect to see something on</text><text start="792.98" dur="5.469">that screen is exactly behind that big barrier
that’s in the middle.</text><text start="798.449" dur="4.58">And somehow, when you actually do the experiment,
you see that actually, that’s where most</text><text start="803.029" dur="1.67">of the particles end up.</text><text start="804.699" dur="3.411">So, it’s always exactly the opposite.</text><text start="808.11" dur="4.699">And you get this weird pattern with other
bands going out.</text><text start="812.809" dur="5.65">And so you initially would stare at it and
shake your head and wonder what you’d actually have.</text><text start="819.46" dur="4.03">So we’ll analyze what that means in just
a moment.</text><text start="823.49" dur="5.18">But I, you know, we often, I don’t know,
probably most everyone in this audience has</text><text start="828.67" dur="5.3">seen a still image or animation like this
in the discussion of quantum mechanics.</text><text start="833.97" dur="3.729">And I thought it would be kind of nice to
show you that it, that this actually happens.</text><text start="837.699" dur="2.461">It’s not just an animation that an artist
does.</text><text start="840.16" dur="5.52">So we’re going to actually do the Double
Slit Experiment, for real, right now.</text><text start="845.68" dur="5.26">And to do that, I’m going to invite a friend
of mine from Princeton University.</text><text start="850.94" dur="8.629">Omalon, can you wheel out, if you would, the
Double Slit Experiment?</text><text start="859.569" dur="12.231">Alright, so what we have here is a laser on
this far side.</text><text start="871.8" dur="1.67">So this is our source.</text><text start="873.47" dur="4.419">So actually we’re doing this in some sense
opposite to the orientation that we saw in</text><text start="877.889" dur="1.26">the animation.</text><text start="879.149" dur="3.88">And we’re going to fire this laser, which
is photons, in essence.</text><text start="883.029" dur="4.321">And the photons are going to go through a
barrier that has two openings in it--it’s</text><text start="887.35" dur="3.109">harder to see that of course mechanically,
but trust me there’s a barrier with two</text><text start="890.459" dur="1">openings.</text><text start="891.459" dur="6">And we’re going to take a look at the data
that falls on a detector screen, which in</text><text start="897.459" dur="4.671">the modern age is a more complicated and somewhat
finicky piece of equipment.</text><text start="902.13" dur="6.369">So we’re all sitting here, on shpilkes,
if you speak any Yiddish, you know exactly</text><text start="908.499" dur="1.631">what I’m talking about right there.</text><text start="910.13" dur="2.22">But hopefully this will work out.</text><text start="912.35" dur="4.02">So, Omalon, why don’t we just actually see
ambient noise.</text><text start="916.37" dur="2.36">Can we see a little bit of that first?</text><text start="918.73" dur="3.029">Can we switch over to the input to the screen?</text><text start="921.759" dur="4.101">Alright so this is the output from that device.</text><text start="925.86" dur="5.3">And now, if we actually turn on the laser
and allow us to collect all the photons that</text><text start="931.16" dur="1.82">land, over time.</text><text start="932.98" dur="3.669">There, they’re building up.</text><text start="936.649" dur="2.281">And there you see what actually happens.</text><text start="938.93" dur="2.23">So this is the result of this very device
here.</text><text start="941.16" dur="2.119">And you see it.</text><text start="943.279" dur="3.781">You can see on the very far left, we see some
of the photons are landing.</text><text start="947.06" dur="2.24">Then we get a dark region in between.</text><text start="949.3" dur="3.88">Then a bright, a dark, a bright, a dark, a
bright, a dark, and a bright and a dark...even</text><text start="953.18" dur="5.579">though this device over here really is a barrier
that has only 2 slits in it.</text><text start="958.759" dur="5.5">So the animation that we showed you actually
does hold true in real experiments.</text><text start="964.259" dur="4.62">And that then forces us to come to grips with
it, to try to understand what in the heck</text><text start="968.88" dur="2.23">is actually going on.</text><text start="971.11" dur="2.29">So, thank you Omalon.</text><text start="975.46" dur="1.09">So there we have it.</text><text start="976.55" dur="6.67">We have this situation in which we expected
to get two bands and we got more.</text><text start="983.22" dur="1.9">What does that tell us?</text><text start="985.12" dur="1.45">Where do we go from there?</text><text start="986.57" dur="6.769">That there’s an existing bit of mathematics
that comes up with exactly that same pattern.</text><text start="993.339" dur="2.5">But it has nothing to do with particles.</text><text start="995.84" dur="6.08">It’s the mathematics that you use to describe
waves, water waves, or other kinds of waves.</text><text start="1001.92" dur="3.68">Yeah. So can we see the animation that has a single?</text><text start="1005.619" dur="5.671">So this is a warm-up to the problem, where
we have water going through a single opening.</text><text start="1011.29" dur="1.79">Just tell us what we see happening here.</text><text start="1013.08" dur="5.38">That’s right, so you’ve got sort of a
water wave, a wave front coming along, and then</text><text start="1018.46" dur="8.42">that slit acts as a bit of a source for
this rippling wave going out in a circular pattern.</text><text start="1027.14" dur="5.86">And you see it’s most wavy at the place
behind the slit on the wall.</text><text start="1033" dur="2.02">That’s indicated by the brightness there.</text><text start="1035.06" dur="5.82">Yeah. And then if we go on to a more relevant version for the actual Double Slit Experiment...</text><text start="1040.89" dur="2.89">Yeah, so now we’ve got that same wave front.</text><text start="1043.78" dur="5.08">But now there’s two slits, and it’s like
there’s two different sources of waves,</text><text start="1048.86" dur="4.17">like if you threw two different pebbles in
the pond at the same time.</text><text start="1053.03" dur="5.05">And what happens is they’re both, you’re
both creating waviness.</text><text start="1058.08" dur="4.66">But some places on the screen, the wave from
one is doing this, and the wave from the other</text><text start="1062.74" dur="3.2">is doing this, and they kind of cancel out.</text><text start="1066.42" dur="4.44">But right there in the middle, what’s happening
is that the wave from the one slit is going</text><text start="1070.86" dur="4.161">up right when the wave from the other slit
is going up, and then they do this, and then</text><text start="1075.021" dur="1.989">you get a big wave and that’s the bright
part.</text><text start="1077.01" dur="5.3">But, if you work out the mathematics, then
the places that have the big waves are exactly</text><text start="1082.31" dur="5.73">these bright ones, and that’s just like
we saw in the Double Slit for the particles.</text><text start="1088.08" dur="7.28">Right. So as Gerard was saying, as Mark was saying,
we now have a strange confluence of two things:</text><text start="1095.37" dur="4.59">the data that comes out of the Double Slit
Experiment when done with particles, and something</text><text start="1099.96" dur="4.61">that seems to have nothing to do with it,
where we just have waves going through a barrier</text><text start="1104.57" dur="1.02">with two openings.</text><text start="1105.59" dur="5.56">So, the conclusion then is that there is some
weird connection between particles and waves,</text><text start="1111.15" dur="2.46">that’s where that connection comes from.</text><text start="1113.61" dur="2.31">And, let’s push that further, so...</text><text start="1115.92" dur="5.08">Yeah. I mean let’s just drive home how weird it
should be that there is any kind of connection here.</text><text start="1121.06" dur="1.64">So imagine I do the Two Slit Experiment.</text><text start="1122.7" dur="1.5">I cover up one of the slits.</text><text start="1124.2" dur="1.77">The effect completely goes away.</text><text start="1125.97" dur="4.081">I get a bit of a spreading out of the particles, but I don’t get that interference.</text><text start="1130.051" dur="1">I don’t get those bands.</text><text start="1131.051" dur="2.079">Much as we saw with water going through a
single opening.</text><text start="1133.13" dur="3.94">Exactly, much as we see with water going through
the single slit, and much as we see with your</text><text start="1137.07" dur="1.45">classical intuition about particles.</text><text start="1138.52" dur="3.61">If I cover up the other slit, exactly the
same result.</text><text start="1142.13" dur="3.6">It’s only if I have both slits open at the
same time that the effect happens.</text><text start="1145.73" dur="4.97">So it seems to be, for all the whirls, if
somehow something’s going through the first slit,</text><text start="1150.84" dur="4.26">and something else is going through
the other slit, and between them they’re</text><text start="1155.1" dur="1.22">interacting to create this strange effect.</text><text start="1156.32" dur="4.7">And that’s why it matters so much, that
I can do this experiment with one particle at a time.</text><text start="1161.06" dur="3.58">If this was just a massive light going through,
no surprise.</text><text start="1164.66" dur="3.36">The sunlight’s going through the left slit,
the sunlight’s going through the right slit.</text><text start="1168.02" dur="1.97">The left-hand light, the right-hand light
interferes.</text><text start="1169.99" dur="4.18">But I can set this stuff up so that only one
photon goes through every hour and a half,</text><text start="1174.17" dur="1">I still see the effect.</text><text start="1175.17" dur="1">It doesn’t go down in its likeness.</text><text start="1176.17" dur="1">Yeah, can we see that?</text><text start="1177.17" dur="0.99">I think we have that--</text><text start="1178.16" dur="3.16">And then you might be thinking, well maybe
each individual particle breaks in half,</text><text start="1181.32" dur="2.9">and half of the particle goes through one slit,
and half of the particle goes through another slit.</text><text start="1184.34" dur="3.16">But again, then you’d think you could--look--then
you’d think you’d be seeing half-strength</text><text start="1187.51" dur="1">detections.</text><text start="1188.51" dur="1.26">But that’s not what you see.</text><text start="1189.77" dur="3.88">Whenever you look, each time you send a particle
through, if you look where it is, you see</text><text start="1193.65" dur="2.75">the particle in one place and one place only.</text><text start="1196.4" dur="5.46">So trying to reconcile those two accounts
of what’s going on makes your mind hurt.</text><text start="1201.9" dur="1.8">Yeah, exactly.</text><text start="1203.7" dur="5.34">So we’re forced into, as David was saying,
not just thinking that a large collection</text><text start="1209.04" dur="4.7">of particles behaves like a wave, which maybe
would not be that surprising because water</text><text start="1213.74" dur="4.36">waves are made of H2O molecules, particles,
and therefore they’re kind of wavy,</text><text start="1218.1" dur="4.08">but each individual particle somehow has a wave-like quality.</text><text start="1222.18" dur="5.44">And historically, people struggled to figure
out what wave, what kind of wave, what</text><text start="1227.62" dur="4.62">is it made of and what does it represent if you have a wave associated with a particle.</text><text start="1232.24" dur="2.84">A wave is spread out, a particle is at a point.</text><text start="1235.08" dur="8.72">And it was Max Born in the 1920’s who came up with the strange idea of what these waves are.</text><text start="1243.8" dur="3.08">So, Birgitta, what are these waves telling
us about?</text><text start="1246.89" dur="8.59">Well the waves, what we see is the probability
which, the square of the wave or the modulus</text><text start="1255.48" dur="1.14">of the wave, but—</text><text start="1256.62" dur="1.641">So here’s a wave behind you.</text><text start="1258.261" dur="2.199">So you said, “probability,” in essence—</text><text start="1260.46" dur="0.66">Yes.</text><text start="1261.12" dur="4.3">This is an amplitude, this is an amplitude
which will give us a probability.</text><text start="1265.42" dur="3.82">If we take this amplitude and look anywhere
here with some measuring device,</text><text start="1269.24" dur="6.58">we will find with some distinct probability, after measuring many times, we’ll find that there’s a</text><text start="1275.82" dur="3.5">definite probability of the particle being
there, just as in the double slit.</text><text start="1279.32" dur="4.14">After sending many particles through, we found
with a certain probability that they would</text><text start="1283.46" dur="2.58">all appear on the left, or all on the right.</text><text start="1286.04" dur="4.2">So, in some sense, vaguely, where the wave
is big,</text><text start="1290.24" dur="2.38">there’s a high likelihood you’re going to find the particle.</text><text start="1292.62" dur="4.65">Where the wave is near zero, there’s a very
small probability that you’re going to find</text><text start="1297.27" dur="0.57">the particle.</text><text start="1297.84" dur="0.84">But you can’t guarantee it.</text><text start="1298.68" dur="4.74">So any one particle could be in a place where
the wave is very very small.</text><text start="1303.42" dur="2.84">Now these are all just pictures.</text><text start="1306.26" dur="4.32">In the 1920s, physicists were able to make
this precise.</text><text start="1310.58" dur="6.13">So Schrodinger wrote down an equation, and
I think we can show you what the equation</text><text start="1316.71" dur="0.59">looks like.</text><text start="1317.3" dur="4.5">Obviously, you don’t need to know the math
to follow anything that we’re talking about here.</text><text start="1321.82" dur="7.2">But Gerard, you wanted to emphasize that there
is math behind this, because your experience</text><text start="1329.02" dur="3.94">has been that many people miss that point,
so feel free to emphasize.</text><text start="1332.96" dur="1.32">Absolutely.</text><text start="1334.28" dur="7.56">Quantum mechanics, when we talk about it,
there is a temptation to keep the discussion very fuzzy.</text><text start="1342.02" dur="5.88">And so I get very many letters by people who have their own ideas about what quantum mechanics is, and</text><text start="1347.9" dur="5.3">they are very good at reproducing
fuzzy arguments, but they come without the</text><text start="1353.2" dur="3.16">equations, or the equations are equally fuzzy
and meaningless.</text><text start="1356.36" dur="5.88">Whereas, the beauty of quantum mechanics is the fundamental mathematical coherence of these equations.</text><text start="1362.24" dur="7.66">You can prove that, if this equation describes
probabilities exactly as you said before,</text><text start="1369.91" dur="6.18">then actually the equations handle probabilities
exactly the way probabilities are supposed</text><text start="1376.09" dur="1.25">to be handled.</text><text start="1377.34" dur="5.32">Except, of course, when two waves reinforce
each other, the probabilities become four</text><text start="1382.66" dur="2.41">times as big rather than twice as big.</text><text start="1385.07" dur="4.87">But a lot of soft spots, the waves annihilate
the probabilities, and so the probabilities</text><text start="1389.94" dur="4.12">become zero where the waves are vanishing.</text><text start="1394.06" dur="4.36">So all this hangs together in a fantastically
beautiful mathematical matter.</text><text start="1398.42" dur="1.3">Now math is one thing.</text><text start="1399.72" dur="1.3">Experiment is another.</text><text start="1401.02" dur="6.78">So how would you test a theory that only gives rise to, Mark, probabilities of one outcome or another?</text><text start="1407.8" dur="2.88">How would you go about determining if it’s
right or if it’s wrong?</text><text start="1410.68" dur="6.96">Yeah, so it’s like if you gave me a coin,
and you said “this is a probabilistic thing.</text><text start="1417.64" dur="4.04">You flip it, it’s going to be heads half
the time and tails half the time.”</text><text start="1421.68" dur="4.66">And I want to check that, I don’t trust
you for--I don’t know why that would be,</text><text start="1426.34" dur="1.12">but--</text><text start="1427.46" dur="1.26">Don’t worry, I’m not insulted.</text><text start="1428.72" dur="7.7">So I just flip the coin, you know, a hundred
thousand times, or whatever.</text><text start="1436.42" dur="3.36">You have a lot of patience to test these things.</text><text start="1439.78" dur="2.04">The more sure I want to be, the more I flip
it.</text><text start="1441.82" dur="3.98">So maybe I do it 10 times and I get 4 and
6, and I’m like, “oh, maybe I’ll flip</text><text start="1445.8" dur="4.38">it a hundred times” and then I get 48 heads
and 52 tails.</text><text start="1450.18" dur="5.42">So I can basically just repeat the experiment
a whole bunch of times, and if I have a very</text><text start="1455.6" dur="5.51">precise prediction from those quantum mechanics
equations to tell me exactly how often I should</text><text start="1461.11" dur="2.55">expect to get one result versus another,</text><text start="1463.66" dur="3.5">So, I think we have, we can give a little
schematic, what are we seeing here?</text><text start="1467.16" dur="0.5">Have a look.</text><text start="1467.66" dur="5.84">Right, so we’re doing, there’s our wave
that’s describing the state of the particle,</text><text start="1473.51" dur="2.03">the thing without a definite location.</text><text start="1475.54" dur="3.14">Then we’re setting that up a whole bunch
of times, and measuring where the particle</text><text start="1478.68" dur="1.41">is each time.</text><text start="1480.09" dur="2.53">And these X’s are showing the results of
our measurement.</text><text start="1482.62" dur="1.52">That’s like flipping your coin and getting
a head or getting a tail.</text><text start="1484.14" dur="2.34">Exactly. So there’s all these possible locations.</text><text start="1486.48" dur="5.3">And what we see is that after a while, the
pattern of how often I get one place versus</text><text start="1491.79" dur="6.42">another place, it’s matching up to that
expectation given by the blue curve, by this</text><text start="1498.21" dur="1">wave, or wave function.</text><text start="1499.21" dur="3.55">That’s right, so we can’t predict the
outcome of any given run of the experiment,</text><text start="1502.76" dur="6.62">but over time, building up the statistics,
we believe the theory if they align with the</text><text start="1509.38" dur="5.18">probability profile given by this wave, whose
equation we showed you, and that is what works</text><text start="1514.57" dur="3.16">out the shape of the wave in any given situation.</text><text start="1517.73" dur="6.15">And just to bring this full circle, if we
look at the Double Slit Experiment in this</text><text start="1523.88" dur="5.72">wave-like language, now think of the electron
or the photon as a wave, it goes through,</text><text start="1529.6" dur="5.03">it interferes like water waves going through
the two openings, and therefore you have an</text><text start="1534.63" dur="3.62">interference pattern on the screen, which
is telling you where it’s bright, it is</text><text start="1538.25" dur="2.5">very likely that you’ll find the particles.</text><text start="1540.75" dur="1.57">Where it’s dark, it’s unlikely.</text><text start="1542.32" dur="3.93">Where it’s black, there’s zero chance
of finding the particle there, and therefore</text><text start="1546.25" dur="4.97">you run this experiment with a lot of particles,
and they’re going to primarily land in the</text><text start="1551.22" dur="1.02">bright regions.</text><text start="1552.24" dur="4.1">They’re going to land somewhat in the greyer regions, and they’re not going to land at all in the black region.</text><text start="1556.44" dur="5.6">And indeed, that’s exactly what we showed
in the experiment that we ran with the double</text><text start="1562.051" dur="1.149">slit just a moment ago.</text><text start="1563.2" dur="2.02">And that’s why we believe these ideas.</text><text start="1565.22" dur="5.94">So that’s, in some sense, really the basics
of quantum mechanics.</text><text start="1571.16" dur="4.8">Classical physics, particle motion, is the
intuitive one described by trajectories.</text><text start="1575.96" dur="3.12">And quantum physics, the particle motion is
somewhat fuzzier.</text><text start="1579.08" dur="6.08">It’s got this probabilistic wave-like character,
and the curious thing about a wave, as sort</text><text start="1585.16" dur="3.5">of a wave of probability, if the wave is spread
out, it means there’s a chance that the</text><text start="1588.66" dur="3.08">particle is here, a chance that it’s here,
a chance that it’s here.</text><text start="1591.75" dur="6.55">And therefore the wave embraces a whole distinct
collection of possibilities all at once.</text><text start="1598.3" dur="3.57">That, in some sense, is really the weirdness
of quantum mechanics.</text><text start="1601.87" dur="2.07">So that’s the basic structure.</text><text start="1603.94" dur="5.74">And now we’re going to move on to our next chapter where we’re going to dig a little bit deeper.</text><text start="1609.68" dur="4.04">We’ll talk about measurement, and also entanglement.</text><text start="1616.4" dur="2.3">And it’s a dead heat.</text><text start="1618.7" dur="2.56">They’re checking the electron microscope.</text><text start="1621.26" dur="4.78">And the winner is...number 3, in a quantum
finish!</text><text start="1626.04" dur="1.4">No fair!</text><text start="1627.44" dur="3.18">You change the outcome by measuring it!</text><text start="1633.18" dur="6.1">Now either we have a very sophisticated audience, or you just love Futurama, I’m not sure which.</text><text start="1639.28" dur="4.44">But this is part of the issue that we now
want to turn to.</text><text start="1643.73" dur="8.29">Which is, if we have a quantum setup, how
do you move from this probabilistic mathematics,</text><text start="1652.02" dur="4.58">saying that the electron say could be here
or here or here with different probabilities,</text><text start="1656.6" dur="4.1">to the definite reality that Mark was describing:
when you actually do an experiment, you find</text><text start="1660.7" dur="2.98">the electron here or here or here.</text><text start="1663.68" dur="3.46">You never find anything a mixture of results.</text><text start="1667.14" dur="5.24">We want to talk about how we navigate going
from the fuzzy probabilistic mathematical</text><text start="1672.38" dur="5.82">description to the single definite reality
of everyday experience.</text><text start="1678.2" dur="4.96">And this is something that many physicists
have contributed to over the years.</text><text start="1683.16" dur="5.14">Again, Niels Bohr, we had a quote from him
early on, and he’s certainly viewed as really</text><text start="1688.3" dur="3.96">one of the founding pioneers of the subject.</text><text start="1692.26" dur="6.3">But let’s now try to go a little bit further
with our understanding of going from</text><text start="1698.56" dur="2.14">the math to reality.</text><text start="1700.71" dur="4.93">And we’re going to follow in, for this part
of the program, really in Niels Bohr’s footsteps,</text><text start="1705.64" dur="4.42">in something called the Copenhagen approach
to quantum physics.</text><text start="1710.06" dur="6.68">So David, can you just begin to take us through,
what was the ideas of collapse of the wave</text><text start="1716.74" dur="3.06">function, in technical language, what are
those ideas all about?</text><text start="1719.8" dur="0.96">So look at it this way.</text><text start="1720.76" dur="3.88">I’ve got my probability wave, which is sort
of humped--let’s just say for one particle--it’s</text><text start="1724.65" dur="2.4">humped over here and it’s humped over here.</text><text start="1727.05" dur="2.641">So there’s kind of two ways I can think
about that.</text><text start="1729.7" dur="2.82">You might say there’s an “and” way and
an “or” way.</text><text start="1732.52" dur="4.94">So I could think of it as saying that the
particle is here and the particle is here.</text><text start="1737.46" dur="4.04">Or you could think of it as saying the particle
is here or the particle is here.</text><text start="1741.5" dur="5.14">And the problem is I kind of need to use both to make sense of quantum mechanics, or so it seems.</text><text start="1746.64" dur="5.5">So, if I try to explain the two-slit experiment, I have to think in the “and” way to start with.</text><text start="1752.14" dur="5.06">I have to think the particle is going
through this slit, “and” it’s going through this slit.</text><text start="1757.2" dur="2.98">Because if it’s just going through this
slit “or” it’s going through this slit,</text><text start="1760.19" dur="2.25">I can close one of the slits, and it wouldn’t
make any little difference.</text><text start="1762.44" dur="4.16">But then as soon as I look where the particle
is, suddenly the “and” way of talking</text><text start="1766.6" dur="4.96">stops making sense, because it doesn’t seem--we’ll
come back to this--but it doesn’t seem as</text><text start="1771.56" dur="3.15">if I see the particle here “and” the particle
here.</text><text start="1774.71" dur="3.39">It seems as if now, I need the “or” way
of thinking.</text><text start="1778.1" dur="6.02">So what came out of the ideas of Bohr and
Heisenberg and people of the 20’s and 30’s was,</text><text start="1784.12" dur="4.7">well there must be some new bit of physics,
some way in which that Schrodinger&amp;#39;s equation</text><text start="1788.83" dur="2.13">we saw earlier isn’t the whole story.</text><text start="1790.96" dur="5.44">So suddenly the wave function stops being
peaked here and here, and it jumps. It collapses.</text><text start="1796.4" dur="2.74">So let’s see a quick picture of that collapse.</text><text start="1799.14" dur="6.72">So if we have a probability wave here, and
this is the “and” description in your</text><text start="1805.86" dur="3.6">language, it could be in these variety of
different locations.</text><text start="1809.46" dur="5.53">And I now undertake a measurement, and I take
that measurement, and it collapses to the</text><text start="1814.99" dur="1">“or” way.</text><text start="1815.99" dur="1.27">It’s only at one of those locations.</text><text start="1817.26" dur="2.28">Yeah. Suddenly it’s here, and the rest of the
wave function is gone.</text><text start="1819.54" dur="6.18">And now if I turn away, and I stop measuring,
it melts back into the probabilistic description,</text><text start="1825.72" dur="6.67">and we’re back to a language that feels
quite unfamiliar with the particle, is in</text><text start="1832.39" dur="3.52">some sense, at all of these locations simultaneously.</text><text start="1835.91" dur="4.95">Now, the issue that it raised is that you
said, “look, we’re going to have to have</text><text start="1840.86" dur="3.1">some other math to make this happen.”</text><text start="1843.96" dur="5.8">So, first, if we just use the Schrodinger
equation, this beautiful equation that was</text><text start="1849.76" dur="4.84">written down, would that be enough to cause
a wave to undergo that kind of transformation?</text><text start="1854.6" dur="1.4">Nice and spread out.</text><text start="1856" dur="3.64">And now, collapses to one location, where
the particle is found.</text><text start="1859.64" dur="2.58">Can the Schrodinger equation do that for us?</text><text start="1862.22" dur="1">Birgitta?</text><text start="1863.22" dur="1">No.</text><text start="1864.22" dur="1">No.</text><text start="1865.22" dur="1">No.</text><text start="1866.22" dur="1">No.</text><text start="1867.22" dur="1.88">No. [to ‘T HOOFT] That means no, right?</text><text start="1869.1" dur="1.17">It means yes?</text><text start="1870.27" dur="1">OK</text><text start="1871.27" dur="4.42">So, like I said, Gerard has distinct views
which are spectacularly interesting.</text><text start="1875.69" dur="2.09">We are going to come to those in just a moment.</text><text start="1877.78" dur="4.54">But let’s now follow the history of the
subject where we’re going to just follow</text><text start="1882.32" dur="3.87">our nose and we look at the equation that
we have and it doesn’t do it.</text><text start="1886.19" dur="4.9">So what, then, do we do to get out of this
impasse?</text><text start="1891.09" dur="6.59">And to make this impasse even a little bit
more compelling, I’m going to take you through</text><text start="1897.68" dur="5.5">one version of this story that I hope will
make the conundrum as sharp as it can be,</text><text start="1903.18" dur="1.78">and then we’ll try to resolve it.</text><text start="1904.96" dur="5.38">So I’m going to take you through a little
example over here, where we have, say, a particle</text><text start="1910.34" dur="1.64">somewhere in Manhattan.</text><text start="1912.7" dur="6.28">And let’s imagine that the probability wave
makes the particle location peak at the Belvedere</text><text start="1918.98" dur="3.74">Castle in Central Park, just randomly chosen.</text><text start="1922.72" dur="5.34">What that would mean is if somehow I had some
measuring device that could work out where</text><text start="1928.07" dur="5.88">the particle is experimentally, observationally,
indeed it would reveal that the particle is</text><text start="1933.95" dur="1.41">at that location.</text><text start="1935.36" dur="6.58">The wave is sharply peaked at that spot, and therefore all the probability is focused right there.</text><text start="1941.94" dur="2.96">That’s quite a straightforward situation.</text><text start="1944.9" dur="8.1">Imagine we do the experiment again, and the
probability wave has a different footprint.</text><text start="1953" dur="2.9">Let’s say it’s way down there at Union
Square.</text><text start="1955.9" dur="6.36">If you follow the same experimental measurement procedure, and you go about figuring out</text><text start="1962.26" dur="5.1">through your observation where the particle is, you find, indeed, there it is, Union Square.</text><text start="1967.36" dur="6.48">The conundrum is the issue that David was
speaking to, where we now have a situation</text><text start="1973.84" dur="4.56">where we don&amp;#39;t have one peak, but two.</text><text start="1978.4" dur="7.22">Now it’s sort of like the particle is at
the Belvedere Castle AND in Union Square.</text><text start="1985.62" dur="8.96">And that’s puzzling, because if you go about looking at the observation, what do you think will happen here?</text><text start="1994.7" dur="3.84">Well the naive thing is, your detector kind
of doesn’t know what to do.</text><text start="1998.54" dur="6.08">It’s sort of caught between the particle
is at Belvedere Castle and it’s at Union Square.</text><text start="2004.62" dur="6.98">But the thing is, nobody has ever found a
detector--well, I should say nobody who is</text><text start="2011.61" dur="3.91">sober has ever found a detector that does
this.</text><text start="2015.52" dur="0.5">Right?</text><text start="2016.02" dur="2.74">This is not what we experience in the real
world.</text><text start="2018.76" dur="2.96">So this is the issue that we have to sort
out.</text><text start="2021.72" dur="4.72">Because that naive picture is not borne out
by experience.</text><text start="2026.44" dur="6.1">And I think many people here and many people
in the community have thought about this.</text><text start="2032.54" dur="5.52">You in particular, David, believe that you
have the solution.</text><text start="2038.06" dur="5.74">It has a long historical lineage, but why
don’t you tell us a little about the approach</text><text start="2043.8" dur="1.96">that you think resolves this?</text><text start="2045.76" dur="1">OK.</text><text start="2046.76" dur="5.04">Let’s start by reminding ourselves, what’s
the problem with just saying the wave function</text><text start="2051.8" dur="3.34">suddenly jumps to being in Belvedere or Union
Square?</text><text start="2055.14" dur="4.039">And the problem is really just that we’d
have to modify the equations of physics at</text><text start="2059.179" dur="1.851">every level to handle that.</text><text start="2061.03" dur="3.52">So the Schrodinger Equation just does not
let that happen.</text><text start="2064.55" dur="3.95">And to put it mildly, we’ve got quite a
lot of evidence for that structure of physics,</text><text start="2068.5" dur="3.92">and for a whole bunch of reasons.</text><text start="2072.42" dur="4.44">Actually trying to change the physics to make that sudden collapse of the wave function physical,</text><text start="2076.86" dur="6.269">and not just, as Gerard was putting 
it, not just as a sort of fuzzy talk,</text><text start="2083.129" dur="1.551">is a really, really difficult problem.</text><text start="2084.68" dur="4.76">But you could say that we have to do that,
because, like Brian was saying, it doesn’t</text><text start="2089.44" dur="2.579">seem we ever see a particle here and here
at the same time.</text><text start="2092.019" dur="6.33">And I think Brian’s joke is about right
to just what our intuition is about what it</text><text start="2098.349" dur="2.151">would be like to see a particle here and here
at the same time.</text><text start="2100.5" dur="2.509">It would be like being really drunk, like
seeing double.</text><text start="2103.009" dur="4.451">But here’s the thing, if you want to work
out what some physical process would be like,</text><text start="2107.46" dur="3.909">and my looking at a particle is just one more
physical process, it turns out intuition is</text><text start="2111.369" dur="2.131">not a very good way to predict what happens.</text><text start="2113.5" dur="4.099">So how do we ask, what would it really be
like to see a particle that’s here and here</text><text start="2117.599" dur="1">at the same time?</text><text start="2118.599" dur="1.671">Well, what does the physics say?</text><text start="2120.27" dur="1.839">I’m just one more measuring device.</text><text start="2122.109" dur="1.651">And the physics says something like this.</text><text start="2123.76" dur="5.32">If I saw the particle here, I’d go into
a state you might call a “seeing the particle here” state.</text><text start="2129.2" dur="4.9">If I look at the particle there, then I’d go into
what you’d call a “seeing the particle there” state.</text><text start="2134.28" dur="5.46">If it’s in both states at the same time,
then I go into both states at the same time.</text><text start="2139.749" dur="5.221">So, being a little loose for the minute, then
I’m now in the state “seeing the particle</text><text start="2144.97" dur="1.97">here” and “seeing the particle there.”</text><text start="2146.94" dur="4.08">And if I tell Brian where the particle is,
because I’m sure he’s fascinated, Brian’s</text><text start="2151.02" dur="3.28">now in the “David says it’s here, David
says it’s there.”</text><text start="2154.3" dur="1.9">And the whole audience would have to listen
to me say this.</text><text start="2156.2" dur="5.18">You’re all now in the “it’s here”
and “it’s there” states at the same time.</text><text start="2161.38" dur="6.42">And the reality is that, even if I don’t
tell you this, uncontrollable effects spread outward.</text><text start="2167.8" dur="3.559">And so, before you know, the whole planet
or the whole solar system is in a “particle</text><text start="2171.359" dur="3.9">was seen here and particle was seen here at
the same time” state.</text><text start="2175.259" dur="3.721">And those two states don’t interact with
each other.</text><text start="2178.98" dur="4.36">They’re way too complicated to do the sorts
of interference experiments we were doing</text><text start="2183.34" dur="2.26">with the two slits. You can’t do a two-slit experiment on the whole planet.</text><text start="2185.6" dur="4.59">And so for all intents and purposes, what
the quantum theory is now describing is two</text><text start="2190.19" dur="7.33">sets of goings on, each of which looks, for
all the world, like the particle being in a definite place.</text><text start="2197.66" dur="3.64">And that’s where the terminology of this
way of thinking about quantum mechanics comes</text><text start="2201.3" dur="2.08">about, the Many Worlds Theory.</text><text start="2203.38" dur="4.08">It was Hugh Everett who said, look, if you
just take quantum mechanics seriously, you’re</text><text start="2207.46" dur="5.559">led to this crazy sounding idea of there being
many parallel goings-on at the same time every</text><text start="2213.019" dur="1.471">time you make a quantum measurement.</text><text start="2214.49" dur="5.89">But the thing I want to stress here, is it’s
not that we say quantum mechanics is weird,</text><text start="2220.38" dur="3.32">but let’s bring in an even weirder idea
out of the realm of science fiction</text><text start="2223.7" dur="1.46">to make it even stranger.</text><text start="2225.17" dur="4.32">It’s, whatever it was saying, and what the
people who have pushed his idea since then</text><text start="2229.49" dur="5.33">have been trying to make precise, is the idea
that the quantum theory itself--that Schrodinger</text><text start="2234.82" dur="6.8">equation itself--when you take it very seriously,
tells you that, not at the fundamental level,</text><text start="2241.63" dur="3.739">not at the level of microscopic physics, but
at the level that we see around us in the</text><text start="2245.369" dur="6.4">everyday, then the physics is describing many
goings-on at the same time.</text><text start="2251.769" dur="5.361">The quantum probability wave carries on being
an “and” wave all the way up.</text><text start="2257.13" dur="3.31">So you’re talking about many universes?</text><text start="2260.44" dur="4.48">So this is where this idea of parallel universes
or many worlds comes from.</text><text start="2264.92" dur="4.379">So, in the example that we were looking at,
there would be, say, if you were undertaking</text><text start="2269.299" dur="3.861">this measurement, there would be “you seeing
the particle at Belvedere,” “you seeing</text><text start="2273.16" dur="4.859">it at Union Square,” and as you said, once
you articulate that, we’re all hearing it,</text><text start="2278.02" dur="4.779">and we’re all going along with you in one
universe and another.</text><text start="2283.8" dur="6.08">So that’s one approach to try to disambiguate
a situation in which the quantum mechanics</text><text start="2289.89" dur="1.53">has many possibilities.</text><text start="2291.42" dur="3.71">You’re saying, “no no, it’s not just
that one of them happens, they all happen.</text><text start="2295.13" dur="2.86">They all just happen to happen in distinct
universes.”</text><text start="2297.99" dur="2.61">And weirdly, that’s a conservative idea.</text><text start="2300.6" dur="1.58">Mathematically conservative.</text><text start="2302.18" dur="2.609">And that’s actually a vital point.</text><text start="2304.789" dur="3.75">So, and this is an idea that is hard to communicate
to a general audience.</text><text start="2308.539" dur="4.08">I’m sure many of you are technically trained,
but those who aren’t: if you stare at the</text><text start="2312.619" dur="4.111">equations of quantum mechanics and just take
them at face value, this seems to be where</text><text start="2316.73" dur="1.66">the math takes you.</text><text start="2318.39" dur="3.37">But does that convince--so are you guys convinced?</text><text start="2321.76" dur="1.5">Birgitta, you—</text><text start="2323.26" dur="3">There are alternative perspectives.</text><text start="2326.26" dur="2.759">But what about--why don’t you like this
one?</text><text start="2329.019" dur="1">I like it.</text><text start="2330.019" dur="1">I think it’s fascinating.</text><text start="2331.019" dur="1">I think it’s wonderful.</text><text start="2332.019" dur="2.211">But let’s bring in some information.</text><text start="2334.23" dur="2.85">So how much information are we going to keep?</text><text start="2337.08" dur="6.18">So this “many worlds” hypothesis would
say that we’re keeping every single piece of information.</text><text start="2343.26" dur="4.779">But if we--so we have a measuring device,
and then the measuring device is interacting</text><text start="2348.04" dur="0.999">with the environment.</text><text start="2349.04" dur="5.78">Then the environment of outside is also playing
a role, it’s also affecting the measuring device.</text><text start="2354.82" dur="7.56">And of these many many options, measurements
that can be recorded by the measuring device--if</text><text start="2362.39" dur="5.129">the environment, which is interacting with
that measuring device, is interacting with</text><text start="2367.519" dur="5.07">that measurement device and producing many
more outcomes, and yet then we throw--in producing</text><text start="2372.589" dur="5.591">much more information, but then we throw all
of that information of the environment away.</text><text start="2378.18" dur="3.829">Then we’re left with something which produces
just one of these options.</text><text start="2382.009" dur="2.801">So you’re talking technical language of
what’s called “decoherence”?</text><text start="2384.81" dur="0.49">Yes.</text><text start="2385.3" dur="5.86">I’m introducing this technical term that
the coherence of the wave function, the preservation</text><text start="2391.16" dur="1.9">of these...</text><text start="2393.06" dur="6.56">So your belief is that if we don’t focus
just on the simple particle itself, but take</text><text start="2399.63" dur="4.489">into account how it talks to and interacts
with the full environment, you feel like that’s</text><text start="2404.119" dur="1.361">enough to solve the conundrum?</text><text start="2405.48" dur="4.139">Well, I’m, there’s also mathematics to
justify this.</text><text start="2409.619" dur="1.071">So this is another perspective.</text><text start="2410.69" dur="2.679">I’m not saying we don’t know it, which
is one.</text><text start="2413.369" dur="4.531">But this is a very strong argument for saying
why we don’t actually experience many, many</text><text start="2417.9" dur="1.139">universes at once.</text><text start="2419.039" dur="1.83">What’s your view on the many—</text><text start="2420.869" dur="3.37">Yeah, I mean, I think it’s what you were
describing.</text><text start="2424.239" dur="5.091">It’s basically just going all in on the
Schrodinger equation, saying, OK, we’ve</text><text start="2429.33" dur="1.709">got this beautiful equation.</text><text start="2431.039" dur="2.531">It applies to the atomic world.</text><text start="2433.57" dur="8.6">Let’s take it seriously and just, if we
believe in it, then not only kind of understand</text><text start="2442.17" dur="4.66">through the mathematics there that at the
local level you would effectively get something</text><text start="2446.83" dur="4.83">like collapse if you look at just a part of
the description of the system.</text><text start="2451.66" dur="6.23">But then the only thing is that, in the end,
it’s a little bit disturbing philosophically</text><text start="2457.89" dur="8.81">that there’s maybe a part of the wave describing
the universe where, you know, I’m a football player, or</text><text start="2466.7" dur="5.56">then that question of well why,
why do, what is our experience in that picture</text><text start="2472.26" dur="1">of many worlds?</text><text start="2473.26" dur="7.04">Is there some way to understand, you know,
why is it that we’re just experiencing one thing and</text><text start="2480.32" dur="7.28">So Gerard, how about--now, I know that you
are going to take us somewhere else now.</text><text start="2487.6" dur="4.86">When you asked me about this question about
the wave function, you were nodding--I was</text><text start="2492.46" dur="3.099">supposed to nod “no,” and I nodded “yes.”</text><text start="2495.56" dur="2.9">And, I caught you off trap for a moment.</text><text start="2498.46" dur="7.86">And the point of this is that the quantum mechanics today is the best we have to do the calculation</text><text start="2506.36" dur="4.62">But the best we have doesn’t mean that the
calculation is extremely accurately correct.</text><text start="2510.98" dur="6.039">So, according to the equations, we get these
many worlds.</text><text start="2517.019" dur="1.621">I agree with that statement.</text><text start="2518.64" dur="4.24">But I don’t agree with the statement that
quantum mechanics is correct, so that we have</text><text start="2522.88" dur="3.709">to accept all these other universes for being
real.</text><text start="2526.589" dur="2.801">No, the calculation is incomplete.</text><text start="2529.39" dur="3.34">There is much more going on that we didn’t
take into account.</text><text start="2532.73" dur="5.629">And then again, you can mention the environment
and other things that you forgot.</text><text start="2538.359" dur="8.031">So, we are so used to physics that unimportant
secondary phenomena can be forgotten, it just</text><text start="2546.39" dur="2.419">leaves out everything taken for granted.</text><text start="2548.809" dur="6.821">But if you do that, you don’t get for certain
what universe you’re in, you get a superposition</text><text start="2555.63" dur="1.75">of different universes.</text><text start="2557.38" dur="6.379">It doesn’t mean that the real outcome that
was really happening is that the universe</text><text start="2563.759" dur="2.871">splits into a superposition of different universes.</text><text start="2566.63" dur="4.76">It means our calculation is inaccurate, and
it could be done better.</text><text start="2571.39" dur="5.159">And that doesn’t mean that our theory is
wrong, but that we made simplifications.</text><text start="2576.549" dur="2.081">We made lots of simplifications.</text><text start="2578.63" dur="6.29">Instead of describing the real world, we split
up the real world in what I call templates.</text><text start="2584.92" dur="5.659">All the particles we talk about are not real
particles, they are just mathematical abstractions</text><text start="2590.579" dur="1.361">of a real particle.</text><text start="2591.94" dur="4.099">We use that because it’s the best we can
do, which is perfect.</text><text start="2596.039" dur="2.45">It’s by far the best we can do.</text><text start="2598.489" dur="3.271">So, in practice, that is just fine.</text><text start="2601.76" dur="3.73">But you just have to be careful in interpreting
your result.</text><text start="2605.49" dur="3.65">The result does not mean that the universe
splits into many other universes.</text><text start="2609.14" dur="4.5">The result means, yes, this answer is the
best answer you can get.</text><text start="2613.64" dur="4.65">Now, look at the amplitude of the universes
that you get out.</text><text start="2618.29" dur="3.779">The one with the biggest amplitude, is most
likely the rightest answer.</text><text start="2622.069" dur="6.92">But, all the other answers could be correct
or could be wrong if we add more details,</text><text start="2628.989" dur="1.691">which we are unable to do.</text><text start="2630.68" dur="3.53">Today, and perhaps also tomorrow.</text><text start="2634.21" dur="6.8">We will also, we will be unable to do it exactly
precisely correctly.</text><text start="2641.01" dur="3.17">So we will have to do with what we’ve got
today.</text><text start="2644.18" dur="2.3">And what we got today is an incomplete theory.</text><text start="2646.49" dur="6.279">We should know better, but unfortunately we
are not given the information that we need</text><text start="2652.769" dur="2.441">to do a more precise calculation.</text><text start="2655.21" dur="4.659">That precise calculation will show wave functions
that do not peak at different points at the</text><text start="2659.869" dur="5.551">same time, like you had in Manhattan at this
address or that address and we are at a superposition.</text><text start="2665.42" dur="6.449">No, in the real world, we are never in a superposition,
because the real world takes every single</text><text start="2671.869" dur="5.291">phenomenon into account, and you cannot ignore
what happens in the environment and so on.</text><text start="2677.16" dur="4.56">If you ignore that, then you get all this
case superposition phenomena.</text><text start="2681.72" dur="5.519">If you were to do the calculation with infinite
precision, which nobody can do, if you calculate</text><text start="2687.24" dur="4.86">everything that happens in this room and way
beyond and take everything into account,</text><text start="2692.1" dur="2.419">you would find a wave function which doesn’t
do that.</text><text start="2694.52" dur="5.76">You would find one which peaks only at the
right answer and gives a zero at the wrong answer.</text><text start="2700.28" dur="1.06">Now, this view...</text><text start="2701.34" dur="7.4">But the theory is so unstable, that the most
minute incorrectness in your calculation gives you these</text><text start="2708.74" dur="6.78">phony signals that say, maybe the universe did this, maybe the universe did that, maybe it did that.</text><text start="2715.76" dur="4.52">Only if you do it precisely correctly, then
you only get one answer.</text><text start="2720.3" dur="0.58">Yeah.</text><text start="2720.88" dur="5.031">Now that resonates obviously with an idea
that goes all the way back to Einstein, that</text><text start="2725.911" dur="1">quantum mechanics was incomplete--</text><text start="2726.911" dur="1">Yes, this is.</text><text start="2727.911" dur="3.009">Yes, I think Einstein would agree with such—</text><text start="2730.92" dur="2.32">Yeah, I think that he would too.</text><text start="2733.24" dur="2.9">Maybe he would have his own ideas.</text><text start="2736.14" dur="7.36">But anyway, to me it sounds like an Einsteinian
attitude.</text><text start="2743.5" dur="1.58">That, no, nature’s absolute.</text><text start="2745.08" dur="0.94">God doesn’t gamble.</text><text start="2746.03" dur="4.16">The gamble is in our calculation, because
we can’t do any better.</text><text start="2750.19" dur="4.829">So let’s take a step back and see why Einstein
came to this conclusion that quantum mechanics</text><text start="2755.019" dur="4.151">is incomplete, which takes us to the next
strangeness of quantum mechanics, which is</text><text start="2759.17" dur="2.25">something called quantum entanglement.</text><text start="2761.42" dur="4.929">So, this is an idea that has a long history
in physics.</text><text start="2766.349" dur="4.92">“I would not call”--entanglement, which
we are about to talk about--”one but rather</text><text start="2771.269" dur="4.741">the characteristic trait of quantum mechanics,
the one that enforces its entire departure</text><text start="2776.01" dur="2.21">from classical lines of thought.”</text><text start="2778.22" dur="4.6">So here’s again one of the founding pioneers
of the theory who thought about this notion</text><text start="2782.82" dur="5.479">that we’re about to describe as the key
element that distinguishes it from our intuition,</text><text start="2788.299" dur="1.091">our classical way of thinking.</text><text start="2789.39" dur="6.459">And as we’ll see, it quickly, in the hands
of Einstein, takes us to a viewpoint that</text><text start="2795.849" dur="2.851">aligns really with what Gerard was saying.</text><text start="2798.7" dur="6.06">And that comes most forcefully in a paper
from 1935, a date that’s good to keep in</text><text start="2804.769" dur="3.391">mind, because we’re going to come back to
it in just a little bit, where these folks</text><text start="2808.16" dur="3.139">write a paper, Einstein, Podolsky, and Rosen.</text><text start="2811.299" dur="6.05">And we can just, this is actually a New York
Times article on it, and you see that they</text><text start="2817.349" dur="6.451">call the theory “not complete,” much as
Gerard was describing.</text><text start="2823.8" dur="4.539">And it’s good to get a feel for why it is
that they came to this conclusion.</text><text start="2828.339" dur="6.41">And it involves this idea of entanglement,
and I’d like us to walk through that, just</text><text start="2834.749" dur="1.32">some of the key steps.</text><text start="2836.069" dur="1.75">And it’s good to do it in the context of
an example.</text><text start="2837.819" dur="2.92">It’s not the example that Einstein and his
colleagues actually used.</text><text start="2840.739" dur="4.911">But it’s an example having to do with a
quality of particles called spin.</text><text start="2845.65" dur="3.33">So just to set it up and then I’ll let the
panelists take it from there.</text><text start="2849" dur="6.44">When we talk about a particle, say, like an
electron, it turns out that has a characteristic called spin.</text><text start="2855.44" dur="2.66">You could think of it almost like a top that’s
spinning around.</text><text start="2858.109" dur="4.18">And roughly speaking, using classical language
to get a feel for it, if the spin, say, is</text><text start="2862.289" dur="1.881">counterclockwise, you say it’s spinning
up.</text><text start="2864.17" dur="2.14">If it’s clockwise, you say it’s spinning
down.</text><text start="2866.31" dur="5.809">And weirdly, a particle can be in a mixture
of being both up and down, using your language</text><text start="2872.119" dur="1.261">of the “and.”</text><text start="2873.38" dur="5.07">And only when you measure the particle, you
find that it snaps out of that mixture, and</text><text start="2878.45" dur="4.899">is at--in the case of the particle in Manhattan,
it was either at one location or another--here</text><text start="2883.349" dur="1.45">it’s one spin or another.</text><text start="2884.799" dur="3">It’s spinning down or up, but it’s definite
after you do the measurement.</text><text start="2887.799" dur="1.151">You never find it in between.</text><text start="2888.95" dur="4.629">Again, you can do a second measurement, and
say it snaps out of this fuzzy haze and it’s</text><text start="2893.579" dur="1">spinning up.</text><text start="2894.58" dur="6.66">And that’s a quality of a single particle
that’s well known in quantum physics.</text><text start="2901.24" dur="6.58">But entanglement arises when you don’t have
one particle, but rather when you have two of them</text><text start="2907.82" dur="2.64">And here’s the weirdness that happens.</text><text start="2910.46" dur="5.12">If you do a measurement in this situation,
even though each particle is 50% up or 50% down,</text><text start="2915.58" dur="3.46">you’d think they’re completely independent,
but you can set these up in such a way that</text><text start="2919.049" dur="5.19">if you do a measurement, it’s always the
case that if the one on the left is up, the</text><text start="2924.239" dur="1.691">one on the right is down.</text><text start="2925.93" dur="2.53">They never are both up or both down.</text><text start="2928.46" dur="4.48">And we can go back to this story again, do
another measurement, and they can be as far</text><text start="2932.94" dur="5.22">apart as you want, and you measure it, and
find, say that the left one is down and the</text><text start="2938.16" dur="1">right one is up.</text><text start="2939.16" dur="6.31">So they’re kind of locked together by a
quantum connection--quantum entanglement--which</text><text start="2945.47" dur="5.779">is graphically what we’re representing by
this yellow line over here.</text><text start="2951.249" dur="4.55">Now, Gerard was talking about incompleteness
of quantum mechanics.</text><text start="2955.799" dur="2.69">What was Einstein’s view of what was going
on here?</text><text start="2958.489" dur="7.071">Well, Einstein’s view was that, really,
what’s going on here is, if you have particles</text><text start="2965.56" dur="3.57">that the math says are both spinning up and
spinning down at the same time, if you could</text><text start="2969.13" dur="4.57">look deeper to the deeper structure that Gerard
was referencing, you’d find that these particles</text><text start="2973.7" dur="1.799">always have a definite spin.</text><text start="2975.499" dur="3.5">They’re not actually going up and down;
that’s just mathematics.</text><text start="2978.999" dur="4.681">They actually have a definite spin and therefore
if you measure them and find that one is up</text><text start="2983.68" dur="1.879">and the other is down, they were already like
that.</text><text start="2985.559" dur="5.321">It’s not as though there was some long distance
connection or communication going on.</text><text start="2990.88" dur="3.4">And this is what’s known as quantum entanglement.</text><text start="2994.28" dur="4.52">And when I describe this to a general audience,
people often get the phenomenon.</text><text start="2998.81" dur="2.549">Yeah, you measure it here, it’s down, you
measure it there, it’s up.</text><text start="3001.36" dur="3.56">But then they always come back to me and say,
“but what’s really going on?”</text><text start="3004.92" dur="2.44">You know, like, but just, “tell me, explain
to me.”</text><text start="3007.369" dur="2.47">I say, “I just did explain to you what’s
going on.</text><text start="3009.839" dur="4.02">That’s all there is--” “No, no,” they
say, “please tell me, how could this be?”</text><text start="3013.86" dur="2.249">So how should we interpret this result?</text><text start="3016.109" dur="5.431">So Einstein says the way you interpret it
is, it was like this the whole time, nothing surprising.</text><text start="3021.54" dur="5.82">But then we try to do experiments and see
if that’s the case and what happens?</text><text start="3027.369" dur="5.791">So there’s a famous person that comes into
the story, who, John Bell.</text><text start="3033.16" dur="3.24">So what is, Mark, what does Bell do for us?</text><text start="3036.4" dur="10.06">I mean, basically, to put it simply, he finds
that any kind of simplistic, Einstein-like</text><text start="3046.46" dur="6.62">description where the thing had the definite
configuration before we did that measurement,</text><text start="3053.08" dur="2.42">it can’t explain the results.</text><text start="3055.5" dur="1">So it just...you can’t...</text><text start="3056.5" dur="2.569">When you say the results you are talking about
observational results.</text><text start="3059.069" dur="1.141">That’s right.</text><text start="3060.21" dur="4.43">Yeah, so he writes this famous paper.</text><text start="3064.64" dur="1.34">What year, is this 1964?</text><text start="3065.98" dur="2.48">I think this...I think it’s like 1964.</text><text start="3068.46" dur="7.02">He writes this famous paper where he surprisingly
is able to get at an experimental consequence</text><text start="3075.48" dur="6.139">of an Einsteinian view, that things are definitely
up or down before you look, it’s just the</text><text start="3081.619" dur="4.531">mathematics that’s giving this weird superposition
quality.</text><text start="3086.15" dur="5.78">And then people go out and ultimately starting,
say, with John Clauser in the, this must be</text><text start="3091.93" dur="2.85">the ‘70s then into the ‘80s with Alain
Aspect.</text><text start="3094.78" dur="7.279">They carry out the measurement, and they find,
as Mark was saying, that the Einsteinian picture</text><text start="3102.06" dur="3.54">doesn’t describe the actual data.</text><text start="3105.6" dur="6.82">So if Einstein were here, I think he’d have
to conclude that, not necessarily that quantum</text><text start="3112.42" dur="7.34">mechanics is complete, but the chink in the
armor that he thought he found isn’t actually correct.</text><text start="3119.76" dur="4.94">So, Gerard, what’s your--because you’re
coming at it from an Einsteinian view--how</text><text start="3124.7" dur="3.27">do you deal with, let’s say this very experiment?</text><text start="3127.97" dur="3.139">May I just add one point of interest?</text><text start="3131.109" dur="6.361">You can think of a classical experiment as
very simple, but not strange at all.</text><text start="3137.47" dur="5.06">Think of--I take two marbles in a black box.</text><text start="3142.53" dur="3.309">One marble is red, the other one is green.</text><text start="3145.839" dur="2.96">Now, I shake the marbles as much as I want.</text><text start="3148.799" dur="4.611">I put--blindfolded, I put one marble in one
box and another marble in the other box.</text><text start="3153.41" dur="3.29">And now I bring these boxes as lightly as
away from each other.</text><text start="3156.7" dur="4.87">As soon as somebody who sits--or say one on
Earth and one on Mars.</text><text start="3161.57" dur="6.51">So somebody on Earth opens this box, and at
the same time the guy on Mars opens his box.</text><text start="3168.1" dur="5.32">Before they opened the box, they didn’t
know what kind of marble they had in there</text><text start="3173.42" dur="1">in the box.</text><text start="3174.42" dur="1.814">Was it the red one, was it the green one,
you don’t know.</text><text start="3176.234" dur="5.456">As soon as the one on Earth opens the box
and says I have the red marble, instantly,</text><text start="3181.69" dur="2.889">the guy on Mars knows he has the green marble.</text><text start="3184.579" dur="2.97">That information went much faster than light.</text><text start="3187.549" dur="4.271">But you also know all this is nonsense, because
they knew it in advance.</text><text start="3191.82" dur="2.959">I had one red, and one green marble.</text><text start="3194.779" dur="1.671">So what’s the big issue?</text><text start="3196.45" dur="1.649">No problem, right?</text><text start="3198.099" dur="5.621">So, the Bell experiment is fundamentally different
from this situation, in the sense that--</text><text start="3203.72" dur="4.21">So what you described, you described sort
of the Einsteinian picture.</text><text start="3207.93" dur="2.049">Einstein would say, don’t get worked up
about entanglement.</text><text start="3209.98" dur="3.08">It’s just like having a green marble or
red marble.</text><text start="3213.06" dur="4.22">Einsteinian picture would work perfectly well
for the box with the red marble and green marble.</text><text start="3217.28" dur="1.64">No sweat, no difficulty.</text><text start="3218.92" dur="1.88">We understand this situation.</text><text start="3220.8" dur="1.46">No miracle at all.</text><text start="3222.26" dur="5.4">But for the Bell Lab experiment with the spinning
particle, you’re using the fact that the</text><text start="3227.66" dur="6.7">particle is a quantum spinning particle, and
a spinning particle is something very, very strange.</text><text start="3234.36" dur="2.739">It can either spin up or spin down.</text><text start="3237.099" dur="2.27">But then someone asked, what about spinning
sideways?</text><text start="3239.369" dur="5.361">Why not rotate the particle 45 degrees or
90 degrees, and they would say “yes, but</text><text start="3244.73" dur="1.9">that’s a quantum superposition.”</text><text start="3246.63" dur="7.739">But, now if the one person on Earth looks
at the particle spinning up, the one on Mars</text><text start="3254.369" dur="5.321">is spinning down, but then when the person
on Earth sees the particle spinning sideways,</text><text start="3259.69" dur="4.629">the guy on Mars sees the particle spinning
sideways in the other direction, and sees</text><text start="3264.319" dur="3.47">it either spinning up or spinning down, we
still don’t know.</text><text start="3267.789" dur="4.99">But when they both look at the sideways direction,
they again see the spin opposite.</text><text start="3272.779" dur="2.32">That is the miracle.</text><text start="3275.1" dur="4.14">That is a thing which is very very difficult
to understand classically.</text><text start="3279.24" dur="4.48">I maintain, but this is my private opinion,
that you can explain it, but it is--</text><text start="3283.72" dur="0.8">How?</text><text start="3284.52" dur="1.4">Because this is where Einstein failed...</text><text start="3285.92" dur="0.98">Because they both have the same origin.</text><text start="3286.9" dur="6.24">They both came eventually from an atom emitting
two spinning objects: two photons, or two</text><text start="3293.15" dur="5.199">electrons or something like that, which were
entangled.</text><text start="3298.349" dur="7.291">So the entanglement can be explained in terms
of correlations, so that the initial state</text><text start="3305.64" dur="3.11">was not that the particle could be doing just
anything.</text><text start="3308.75" dur="2.94">No, there are correlations all over the place.</text><text start="3311.69" dur="6.77">This is very, very difficult to explain, and
I even wouldn’t dare to try to go in depth,</text><text start="3318.46" dur="2.82">but the answer lies in correlations.</text><text start="3321.28" dur="1.88">Do you think there is a way out of this impasse?</text><text start="3323.17" dur="1.03">I think there is a way out.</text><text start="3324.2" dur="9.039">But it’s extremely non-trivial, and if you
don’t do it quite right, you end up mystified</text><text start="3333.24" dur="0.98">by the situation.</text><text start="3334.22" dur="7.12">It is actually also extremely hard to make
a model that works, that gives this strange-looking phenomenon.</text><text start="3341.64" dur="6.06">So yes, we have a problem, but now I think
the problem has an answer, but the answer</text><text start="3347.7" dur="4.659">is very difficult and you have to work very
hard to make it all hang together properly.</text><text start="3352.359" dur="3.301">That will be in the footnotes of tonight’s
program.</text><text start="3355.66" dur="1.72">You’ll receive it in your email.</text><text start="3357.38" dur="2.86">So David, your view on entanglement?</text><text start="3360.24" dur="2.039">Is there a mystery here, or…?</text><text start="3362.28" dur="5.14">There’s a kind of mystery, and it can link
to our earlier mysteries.</text><text start="3367.42" dur="2.02">Look at it this way.</text><text start="3369.44" dur="6.24">My wave--my probability wave for the two spinning
particles, you can kind of describe it as</text><text start="3375.681" dur="4.798">something like half is this--down up--and
half is this--up down.</text><text start="3380.479" dur="3.58">And again we can ask this--well do I want
to think about it as an “and” or an “or”?</text><text start="3384.059" dur="6.441">Do I want to say, well, it’s this “or”
it’s this, or do I somehow have to say it’s</text><text start="3390.5" dur="1.329">this “and” it’s this.</text><text start="3391.829" dur="3.74">Now if it’s this “or” this, that’s
Gerard’s case.</text><text start="3395.569" dur="1.871">That’s not mysterious at all.</text><text start="3397.44" dur="3.079">And that’s exactly what Einstein, Podolsky,
and Rosen hoped was the case.</text><text start="3400.52" dur="6.88">But what Bell’s results show us is that
the “this OR this” reading of entanglement,</text><text start="3407.4" dur="6.34">just like in some ways the “this slit OR
this slit” reading of the two-slit experiment</text><text start="3413.749" dur="3.77">would lead to experiment predictions that
don’t pan out.</text><text start="3417.519" dur="5.32">We can’t, at least straightforwardly, we
can’t make sense of the experiments without</text><text start="3422.839" dur="4.16">seeing the entangled system as being this
“and” this.</text><text start="3426.999" dur="4.34">And now we’re right back to the mystery,
because understanding how it can be this “and”</text><text start="3431.339" dur="5.411">this, which seems to imply some sort of deep
connection between the two systems, where</text><text start="3436.75" dur="4.89">somehow saying everything there is about this
side, and everything there is about this side</text><text start="3441.64" dur="2.13">separate doesn’t tell you anything.</text><text start="3443.77" dur="1.74">That weird reading seems compulsory.</text><text start="3445.51" dur="1">Right.</text><text start="3446.51" dur="3.19">So, Birgitta, your view on this?</text><text start="3449.7" dur="2.2">Should we fret about entanglement?</text><text start="3451.9" dur="1.55">Is it—</text><text start="3453.45" dur="2.039">I think Gerard raised a very important point.</text><text start="3455.489" dur="5.671">It’s that when one talks about entanglement,
one should not forget to say how the particles</text><text start="3461.16" dur="1.24">got entangled.</text><text start="3462.4" dur="2.3">And they get entangled through an interaction.</text><text start="3464.7" dur="5.289">And I think, to most physicists, entanglement
is not so mysterious if we think about it</text><text start="3469.989" dur="4.23">in those terms, even in just atomic or molecular
terms.</text><text start="3474.22" dur="3.6">So you take the two electrons in the helium
atom.</text><text start="3477.82" dur="4.919">In the ground state, the helium atom is--if
we were to separate the two electrons—we</text><text start="3482.74" dur="3.54">know we can’t do that, because they’re
sitting on top of each other.</text><text start="3486.28" dur="4.54">But were you able to take those two electrons
and pull them apart, they would be in a perfectly</text><text start="3490.82" dur="1.94">entangled pair.</text><text start="3492.76" dur="4.329">But we know how they got there, because they
had an interaction that put them into a particular</text><text start="3497.089" dur="2.391">electronic state.</text><text start="3499.48" dur="5.26">And so if you randomly just put two particles
together, they would not be entangled necessarily.</text><text start="3504.74" dur="0.72">Yeah.</text><text start="3505.46" dur="3.98">To my mind, though, the very fact that--I
don’t care how you set it up, the fact that</text><text start="3509.44" dur="6.029">you CAN set it up still makes me, in Niels
Bohr’s language, “dizzy.”</text><text start="3515.469" dur="5.261">But yes, I agree that does mitigate it to
some extent, but still, it’s so far outside</text><text start="3520.73" dur="3.43">of common experience that it’s still hard
to grasp.</text><text start="3524.16" dur="3.5">But for these purposes, let’s assume entanglement
is real.</text><text start="3527.66" dur="6.47">Because now we want to move on to think about
how it manifests itself in some unusual places</text><text start="3534.13" dur="2.85">like in the vicinity of a black hole.</text><text start="3536.98" dur="4.06">So that’s the next thing that we’re going
to turn to.</text><text start="3541.04" dur="5.6">And for that extent let’s move on to the
next section-- “Quantum Mechanics and Black Holes.”</text><text start="3546.64" dur="4.04">And we’ll also begin with a little clip.</text><text start="3553.6" dur="2.58">Lisa, do you have a stray dog down there?</text><text start="3556.18" dur="3.06">Um, it’s a lot worse than a stray dog.</text><text start="3559.24" dur="1.52">Two stray dogs?</text><text start="3560.76" dur="1.56">It’s a black hole!</text><text start="3562.32" dur="1.42">That was going to be my next guess.</text><text start="3563.74" dur="3.46">Are you sure your next guess wasn’t “three
stray dogs”?</text><text start="3567.2" dur="1.02">Maybe.</text><text start="3570.1" dur="1.879">Alright, so black holes.</text><text start="3571.979" dur="2.78">I think most people here are quite familiar
with what they are.</text><text start="3574.759" dur="4.79">But just again, to get us on the same page,
Mark, just describe what is a black hole.</text><text start="3579.549" dur="6.27">Yeah, so it comes out of Einstein’s picture
of gravity and how the space we live in is</text><text start="3585.819" dur="5.421">not sort of a passive background, but it’s
dynamical, it can warp and bend and it does</text><text start="3591.24" dur="4.539">that kind of in response to the mass and energy
that’s in the universe.</text><text start="3595.779" dur="4.401">And the black hole is the situation where
you take that to the extreme.</text><text start="3600.18" dur="6.25">You have, so much matter--could be a gigantic
star at the end of it’s life when it has</text><text start="3606.43" dur="2.67">burned up it’s fuel and it starts to collapse.</text><text start="3609.1" dur="7.18">And as it’s getting denser and denser, warping
the space more and more, through Einstein’s picture.</text><text start="3616.28" dur="6.88">And at some point, you get this space--the
space time is warped so much, that you get</text><text start="3623.16" dur="5.149">the thing we call a horizon, you get the point
of no return where if you go past that, you</text><text start="3628.309" dur="5.41">can’t get out, you can’t send signals
out, light can’t get out, and that’s our</text><text start="3633.72" dur="1.329">basic notion of a black hole.</text><text start="3635.049" dur="5.091">Now there are many puzzles about black holes,
and some of them are right at the forefront of research.</text><text start="3640.14" dur="4.68">One in particular that I want to focus on
as it will bring together these ideas of entanglement</text><text start="3644.829" dur="3.18">and ultimately the structure of spacetime,
which is where we’ll get to in the next</text><text start="3648.009" dur="5.551">chapter, which is simply this--if something
falls into a black hole, what happens to the</text><text start="3653.56" dur="1.799">information it contained?</text><text start="3655.36" dur="0.9">Right?</text><text start="3656.26" dur="4.9">So to just be concrete, imagine if I was to
take out my wallet and throw it into a black hole.</text><text start="3661.16" dur="3.94">My wallet has all sorts of information, my
credit card information--oh, there it is.</text><text start="3665.109" dur="3.88">They took it out of my pocket, they throw
it into the black hole, it crosses over the</text><text start="3668.989" dur="2.911">horizon, the edge that Mark was referring
to.</text><text start="3671.9" dur="5.68">And at least in the non-quantum, the classical
description, it’s just gone, right?</text><text start="3677.58" dur="4.68">And then you can think that the information
is sort of, maybe still there, it’s just</text><text start="3682.269" dur="1.161">on the other side.</text><text start="3683.43" dur="1.839">We can’t get at it, unless we go in.</text><text start="3685.269" dur="4.07">But if we do that, there are consequences--we
can’t come back out with the information.</text><text start="3689.339" dur="4.52">You know, so that’s sort of the classical
story.</text><text start="3693.859" dur="6.531">This becomes a really big puzzle and a bigger
puzzle when we include quantum mechanics into</text><text start="3700.39" dur="6.469">the story, because of a result that was due
to a couple of very insightful physicists--one</text><text start="3706.859" dur="3.25">who you may not have heard of, one who you
will have heard of.</text><text start="3710.109" dur="8.67">So, back in the ‘70s, Jacob Bekenstein,
and also this fellow over here, Stephen Hawking.</text><text start="3718.779" dur="7.731">They began to apply quantum ideas to black
holes, and found a surprising result, which</text><text start="3726.51" dur="3.12">is that black holes are not actually completely
black.</text><text start="3729.63" dur="4.339">So anyone just jump in and--what is it that
that means?</text><text start="3733.969" dur="1.571">Or Mark, go ahead.</text><text start="3735.54" dur="7.84">So Hawking found, when you start to apply
quantum mechanics to the physics in the vicinity</text><text start="3743.38" dur="8.66">of a black hole, that there are quantum effects
that lead to the black hole seeming to emit</text><text start="3752.04" dur="1.38">particles out of it, as if--</text><text start="3753.42" dur="1.949">Yeah, I think we have a little picture that
can help.</text><text start="3755.369" dur="4.911">Yeah, so this sort of a quantum effect where
you have something happening right at the</text><text start="3760.28" dur="5.56">horizon of the black hole where what we would
call virtual particle and an antiparticle, they—</text><text start="3765.96" dur="1.399">The particle that is red, and the particle
that is blue--</text><text start="3767.359" dur="2.19">Virtual particle is red, and the antiparticle
is blue.</text><text start="3769.549" dur="5.3">This can happen in quantum mechanics, but
because of the black hole horizon, the particles</text><text start="3774.849" dur="2.973">end up going out, and so what it looks like--</text><text start="3777.822" dur="1.707">And their partners fell in, they went out.</text><text start="3779.529" dur="1.241">We don’t see those partners—</text><text start="3780.77" dur="3.38">Which would mean, from far away, if we look
at this situation...</text><text start="3784.15" dur="1.309">That’s right.</text><text start="3785.46" dur="0.999">So there we go.</text><text start="3786.46" dur="4.2">So the black hole looks like it’s emitting
stuff, and it’s actually losing some of its mass.</text><text start="3790.66" dur="2.179">So you see it’s getting smaller.</text><text start="3792.839" dur="4.141">Hawking did a detailed calculation to show
that it’s behaving like an object that’s</text><text start="3796.98" dur="5.29">getting hotter and hotter and hotter, and
sort of what you’d call evaporating more</text><text start="3802.27" dur="3.699">and more quickly, and ultimately disappearing.</text><text start="3805.969" dur="8.31">So all of this information that might have
been in the black hole, it’s now this heat,</text><text start="3814.28" dur="3.9">the thermal radiation going out into space.</text><text start="3818.18" dur="3.359">And all this is happening, if I understand--so
you got the edge of the black hole, you got</text><text start="3821.54" dur="3.14">this quantum process right at the edge that
we’re familiar with.</text><text start="3824.68" dur="1.96">Particle and anti-particle sort of pop out
of empty space.</text><text start="3826.64" dur="4.4">The difference is, now with the black hole
there, it can kind of pull on one member of</text><text start="3831.04" dur="5.34">the pair, get sucked in, the other just rushes
out, and that gives rise to radiation flying outward.</text><text start="3836.38" dur="4.64">And that’s what makes this puzzle sharp,
because if the wallet goes into the black</text><text start="3841.03" dur="4.489">hole, and then you have this radiation coming
out, ultimately, and perhaps the black hole</text><text start="3845.52" dur="1.74">even disappears through this.</text><text start="3847.26" dur="5.46">Everything that went in has come out, but
if the radiation itself doesn’t have an</text><text start="3852.72" dur="5.1">imprint of the wallet, doesn’t somehow embody
the information, the information would be lost.</text><text start="3857.84" dur="4.58">Hawking’s calculation showed that, it should
not matter what formed the black hole.</text><text start="3862.42" dur="1.78">You get the exactly the same radiation.</text><text start="3864.2" dur="4.71">But whether it’s my wallet or whether it’s
a refrigerator, chicken soup, it all would</text><text start="3868.91" dur="1.74">sort of come out the same.</text><text start="3870.65" dur="0.67">The information is lost.</text><text start="3871.32" dur="2.539">Now this disturbed Gerard deeply.</text><text start="3873.86" dur="2.489">Very much so.</text><text start="3876.88" dur="8.359">But the statement you just made was only about
the average Hawking particle.</text><text start="3885.239" dur="4.691">The Hawking particles form what you call a
thermal spectrum, which means that they come</text><text start="3889.93" dur="3.33">out in a completely fundamentally chaotic
way.</text><text start="3893.26" dur="5.18">But it doesn’t mean that they don’t know
in what way they come out.</text><text start="3898.44" dur="5.2">Again, it’s quantum mechanics, but again
there is a theory on the line of quantum mechanics</text><text start="3903.64" dur="5.24">which is more precise, and which we should
provide the missing information.</text><text start="3908.88" dur="6">And yes, there was missing information, and
yes your wallet does leave an imprint on the</text><text start="3914.88" dur="0.96">radiation coming out...</text><text start="3915.84" dur="1.16">So can we show--?</text><text start="3917" dur="5.88">...Because your wallet, yes, if you want to
have a moment, your wallet carries a gravitational</text><text start="3922.88" dur="6.98">field, even though it’s very light compared
to a planet or a star, it does have gravity.</text><text start="3929.86" dur="6.08">That gravity is sufficient to leave a very
minute imprint on the outgoing particles.</text><text start="3935.94" dur="0.88">And that’s enough...</text><text start="3936.82" dur="4.159">So we sort of see that imprint here of my
wallet on the edge of the black hole.</text><text start="3940.979" dur="5.901">The effect of this is that the information
gets stuck on the horizon of the black hole,</text><text start="3946.88" dur="5.26">ready to come out again in the form of the
Hawking particles.</text><text start="3952.14" dur="2.86">And this, in principle, you can compute.</text><text start="3955.009" dur="7.32">And you find that the culprit is the gravitational
field of your wallet, that many people forget</text><text start="3962.329" dur="0.911">to take into account.</text><text start="3963.24" dur="1.18">Then you get a tremendous problem.</text><text start="3964.42" dur="4.899">You don’t understand how can it be that
all those dollars in your--and those credit</text><text start="3969.32" dur="2.78">cards in your wallet, that information gets
out.</text><text start="3972.1" dur="7.259">Well, a normal person would never be able
to identify, to decompose Hawking radiation</text><text start="3979.359" dur="1.331">to get back your wallet.</text><text start="3980.69" dur="4.99">So surely, it’s a better shredder you’ll
never find anywhere, but even the shredder</text><text start="3985.68" dur="1.279">still contains the information.</text><text start="3986.959" dur="1">Right.</text><text start="3987.959" dur="3.1">So people won’t actually be able to do this
reconstruction, but in principle...</text><text start="3991.059" dur="1.42">No, in practice, of course you won’t.</text><text start="3992.479" dur="4.81">...just like with the shredder, in principle
they would be able to do that.</text><text start="3997.289" dur="6.02">So this is an idea that you developed also
with Lenny Susskind, which gives rise to what</text><text start="4003.309" dur="3.671">we call the holographic principle, the holographic
description.</text><text start="4006.98" dur="5.8">Again, because if information is stored on
a thin surface at the edge of the black hole,</text><text start="4012.78" dur="5.78">it sort of brings to mind a hologram, which
is a thin piece of plastic which has etchings on it.</text><text start="4018.56" dur="2.999">When you illuminate it correctly it yields
a three-dimensional entity.</text><text start="4021.559" dur="4.921">Here, you’ve got information on this thin
two-dimensional surface, which is able to</text><text start="4026.48" dur="2.35">reconstruct the object that went in.</text><text start="4028.83" dur="3.389">And that’s why this word “holography”
is used.</text><text start="4032.22" dur="3.38">So this is sort of a deep insight which has
been generalized.</text><text start="4035.6" dur="5.14">People, Gerard and Lenny and others, think
that perhaps the right way of thinking about</text><text start="4040.749" dur="5.631">the universe in any environment, even right
here on Earth, there’s a description where</text><text start="4046.38" dur="6.099">data exists on a thin two-dimensional bounding
surface, which would make us the holographic</text><text start="4052.479" dur="6.53">projections, using this language, of this
information that exists on a thin surface</text><text start="4059.009" dur="4.371">that you wouldn’t think would even have
the capacity to store enough information to</text><text start="4063.38" dur="4.979">make it adequate to describe all the comings
and goings in this three-dimensional realm.</text><text start="4068.359" dur="1">Yes, David?</text><text start="4069.359" dur="4.76">Yeah, I just want to sort of pin down for
a moment, like, why should we care in the</text><text start="4074.119" dur="2.511">first place that the information was lost?</text><text start="4076.63" dur="5.69">We’ve- but by assuming the information was
not being lost, we’ve made our way to remarkable</text><text start="4082.32" dur="1.48">new ideas in physics.</text><text start="4083.8" dur="2.32">And I think there’s a somewhat of a temptation
to think, “well yeah, maybe that’s the</text><text start="4086.13" dur="1">wrong lesson.</text><text start="4087.13" dur="1.83">Maybe what we should learn is information
disappears sometimes.</text><text start="4088.96" dur="1.2">Deal with it.”</text><text start="4090.16" dur="1">Which is what Hawking said.</text><text start="4091.16" dur="1.369">Which is what Hawking himself thought, exactly.</text><text start="4092.529" dur="2.751">And there’s still a minority of people in
physics who take that line.</text><text start="4095.28" dur="2.28">And I think the deeper reason to think why--</text><text start="4097.569" dur="1.691">But Hawking doesn’t take that line in the
end.</text><text start="4099.26" dur="0.78">Hawking changed his mind.</text><text start="4100.04" dur="0.5">Right.</text><text start="4100.54" dur="3.34">And I think the deeper reason to see why the
information being lost is such a problem is,</text><text start="4103.88" dur="3.87">it goes back to where we started, the idea
that black holes are hot, that everything</text><text start="4107.75" dur="4.87">else in the universe that we know is hot has
a story to tell about why it’s hot</text><text start="4112.62" dur="5.78">but basically says it can be in zillions and zillions
and zillions of states, and by statistically</text><text start="4118.4" dur="3.279">averaging over all those states, we get out
the hot behavior.</text><text start="4121.679" dur="4.451">That’s how thermodynamics is grounded in
microscopic physics for every other hot thing</text><text start="4126.13" dur="1.31">in the universe.</text><text start="4127.44" dur="5.739">If information is lost forever in black holes,
then black holes are hot for a fundamentally</text><text start="4133.179" dur="3.501">different reason than why everything else
in the universe is hot.</text><text start="4136.68" dur="4.6">And this whole story about holography and
about information being preserved is basically</text><text start="4141.28" dur="4.339">a bet, and it seems to me a very well-motivated
bet on the idea that black holes are hot for</text><text start="4145.62" dur="1.7">the same reason everything else is hot.</text><text start="4147.32" dur="1.2">Right.</text><text start="4148.52" dur="6.16">So, again, one way of saying that is, when
a black hole is radiating, it’s radiating</text><text start="4154.68" dur="5.54">because, in some sense, stuff is burning near
the edge, even though all the matter that</text><text start="4160.23" dur="2.02">fell in is compressed at the center.</text><text start="4162.25" dur="5.589">And that’s unfamiliar, because, when a star
burns, it’s burning at its surface, so the</text><text start="4167.84" dur="4.84">stuff responsible, the fuel, is burning right
where the radiation is emitted.</text><text start="4172.68" dur="5.24">But with a black hole, all of the fuel, the
mass, is here, whereas the radiation is coming</text><text start="4177.929" dur="1.29">out over here.</text><text start="4179.219" dur="4.52">And that distinction might suggest that it’s
a different kind of burning, but you’re</text><text start="4183.74" dur="0.78">absolutely right.</text><text start="4184.52" dur="3.94">We want all the usual ideas of physics
to work, it better be the same kind of burning.</text><text start="4188.46" dur="3.92">And that’s what the approach of holography
provides for us.</text><text start="4192.38" dur="3.94">And what I’d like to do now is if we can
jump actually to the next chapter, just because</text><text start="4196.321" dur="1.689">time is a little bit short.</text><text start="4198.01" dur="3.01">I want to take this idea of entanglement,
and Mark...</text><text start="4201.02" dur="3.34">Let me just introduce that a little bit.</text><text start="4204.36" dur="5.66">One of the things--you know, Hawking did his
calculation in an approximation, where he</text><text start="4210.02" dur="3.38">didn’t have a theory that actually combined
gravity and quantum mechanics.</text><text start="4213.4" dur="4.049">He was using bits of quantum mechanics and
Einstein’s theory and coming up with this</text><text start="4217.449" dur="2.831">result that you lose information.</text><text start="4220.28" dur="4.319">And if that were true, it would say that gravity
and quantum mechanics are incompatible.</text><text start="4224.6" dur="5.7">You have to change quantum mechanics somehow,
but in quantum mechanics, you never lose information.</text><text start="4230.3" dur="10.2">And so this is why this holographic insight
of Gerard and others is so important.</text><text start="4240.5" dur="6.56">It sort of has given us a way of avoiding
Hawking’s conclusions, and Hawking has accepted that.</text><text start="4247.1" dur="6.66">And so, this way--there’s now--it’s been
for the past 20 years, we’ve got a way of</text><text start="4253.77" dur="4.139">doing quantum gravity, of combining gravity
and quantum mechanics.</text><text start="4257.909" dur="4.351">And it uses this holographic idea in a completely
essential way.</text><text start="4262.26" dur="4.44">And it was like that picture of the Earth
with the data around it.</text><text start="4266.7" dur="5.84">It’s kind of like saying that our reality
that we experience, this gravitational universe</text><text start="4272.54" dur="6.199">that we’re in, there’s kind of an underlying
reality which you can think of as those bits,</text><text start="4278.739" dur="4.4">those 1’s and 0’s on the surface surrounding
us.</text><text start="4283.14" dur="3.26">And that’s what Brian was referring to as
the holograms.</text><text start="4286.4" dur="5.339">So somehow if you want to understand the quantum
mechanics of a system with, say, black holes</text><text start="4291.739" dur="5.221">and gravity, what you really want to do is
understand the quantum mechanics of that hologram,</text><text start="4296.96" dur="7.08">and not kind of directly trying to the calculations
like Hawking did of the black hole.</text><text start="4304.04" dur="3.64">So it’s a very powerful--we’ll come to
you in half a second to summarize that, but--it’s</text><text start="4307.69" dur="2.679">a very powerful dictionary, in some sense.</text><text start="4310.369" dur="3.691">You now have two ways of describing a given
physical system.</text><text start="4314.06" dur="3.329">You can describe it sort of in the conventional
way that we’ve always thought about it as</text><text start="4317.389" dur="3">a three-dimensional world that has comings
and goings.</text><text start="4320.389" dur="3.391">Or you have an alternative language if you
want to make use of it,</text><text start="4323.78" dur="4.2">which is the physics that takes place on this thin bounding surface.</text><text start="4327.98" dur="4.92">And sometimes, that latter description gives
you insights that are very difficult to obtain</text><text start="4332.9" dur="2.88">from the traditional description.</text><text start="4335.78" dur="1.83">And we’re going to come to a version of
that in just a moment.</text><text start="4337.61" dur="1">But yeah, Gerard.</text><text start="4338.61" dur="5.069">Yeah, I think you can make the picture a little
bit more clear perhaps by realizing that whenever</text><text start="4343.679" dur="5.741">you throw something into the black hole, when
you look at it from the outside, you will</text><text start="4349.42" dur="2.759">never actually see it pass through the horizon.</text><text start="4352.18" dur="2.42">It hangs around at the horizon.</text><text start="4354.6" dur="6.3">So it shouldn’t be too surprising that that
information also hangs around at the horizon.</text><text start="4360.9" dur="1.72">So can I just flesh it out for half a second?</text><text start="4362.62" dur="4.599">So what Gerard is saying is, if you look at
how a black hole affects the passage of time,</text><text start="4367.219" dur="4.23">you find that as a clock gets closer and closer
to the edge of a black hole, the clocks ticks</text><text start="4371.449" dur="1.641">off time ever more slowly.</text><text start="4373.09" dur="6.7">So if you’re watching this from very far
away, the object is starting to go in slow</text><text start="4379.79" dur="2.86">motion as it goes toward the edge of the black
hole.</text><text start="4382.65" dur="2.21">It doesn’t just immediately go over the
edge.</text><text start="4384.86" dur="5.18">In fact, it goes so slow that it would take
an infinite amount of time from your perspective</text><text start="4390.04" dur="1.11">for it to actually fall over the edge.</text><text start="4391.15" dur="1">So it hangs out there.</text><text start="4392.15" dur="2.68">The observers there would think that the clock
was standing still.</text><text start="4394.83" dur="5.49">But the clock is simply slowing the time that
the observer, who goes with the clock, sees</text><text start="4400.32" dur="2.169">that “oh, that’s time I’m going through
the horizon.”</text><text start="4402.489" dur="4.991">But, for the outside the observer, that’s
the eternal time, it never changes anymore.</text><text start="4407.48" dur="5.389">The other observation one could make is, it’s
a very elementary calculation to find out</text><text start="4412.869" dur="4.091">how much, how can it put other kinds of information
in such a box?</text><text start="4416.96" dur="4.17">Take a box with a certain radius--or let it
be spherical for simplicity.</text><text start="4421.13" dur="4.319">And ask, how much information can I put in
the box no matter what I do?</text><text start="4425.449" dur="6.391">So take a gas, or take a liquid, or take a
dictionary, throw anything in a box,</text><text start="4431.84" dur="2.72">when do I get the maximum amount of information?</text><text start="4434.56" dur="4.639">You can calculate that, and what you find
is, if you try to put more things in the box,</text><text start="4439.199" dur="6.671">that takes so much energy that those encyclopedias
that you try to put in this box will automatically</text><text start="4445.87" dur="1.66">make a black hole.</text><text start="4447.53" dur="3.959">And what is the object that contains the most
information that you could ever imagine?</text><text start="4451.489" dur="1">It’s the black hole.</text><text start="4452.489" dur="1.561">It always wins.</text><text start="4454.05" dur="2.2">So, the black hole is the maximum.</text><text start="4456.25" dur="5.599">There is no way, no matter what you put in
the box with a given radius, to get more information</text><text start="4461.849" dur="2.681">in that box than what fits on the surface.</text><text start="4464.53" dur="2.649">And that’s the holographic principle.</text><text start="4467.179" dur="2.75">Information is two-dimensional, not three-dimensional.</text><text start="4469.929" dur="7.331">And that is very strange, so that’s why
I call it holography.</text><text start="4477.26" dur="6.04">It is as if, you know, we have a three-dimensional
world, but you take a picture with the machinery</text><text start="4483.3" dur="1">of holography.</text><text start="4484.3" dur="1">I don’t really know.</text><text start="4485.3" dur="3.33">It is a camera which makes a picture, and
if you look at the picture from different</text><text start="4488.63" dur="3.46">angles it looks like reconstructing the three-dimensional
object.</text><text start="4492.09" dur="2.569">But it only exists on a two-dimensional surface.</text><text start="4494.659" dur="3.031">So did you doubt this idea, when you first,
or was it?</text><text start="4497.69" dur="4.719">Yeah, this is, in the discussion with Lenny
Susskind, the word “holography” came up.</text><text start="4502.409" dur="2.881">Right, but were you certain that this was
right when it popped out?</text><text start="4505.29" dur="2.26">Or was this so strange that you were…?</text><text start="4507.55" dur="5">Well, no, it is very strange, but this comes
out of the calculation, must be true.</text><text start="4512.55" dur="2.29">But it’s very counterintuitive.</text><text start="4514.84" dur="0.76">Yeah, yeah.</text><text start="4515.6" dur="3.18">It’s like saying our reality is not as real
as we think it is.</text><text start="4518.78" dur="3.46">Yeah, right, yeah, which for most of us is
pretty odd.</text><text start="4522.24" dur="2.5">So the question is, what happened to the rest
of the information.</text><text start="4524.74" dur="5.3">The three-dimensional information doesn’t
disappear, doesn’t get lost, this is the</text><text start="4530.04" dur="3.16">mysterious aspect of our space time.</text><text start="4533.2" dur="5.32">So let’s take this holographic idea, and
push it one step further, which, Mark, you</text><text start="4538.52" dur="0.92">have been pioneering.</text><text start="4539.44" dur="1.08">Yeah, I mean, so if we take it seriously then...</text><text start="4540.52" dur="3.219">But let me--before we get that, because there’s
one thing that we didn’t discuss that would</text><text start="4543.739" dur="5.141">be useful, and it’s right here, which is,
something else that happened in 1935, which</text><text start="4548.88" dur="1.75">is the idea of wormholes.</text><text start="4550.63" dur="2.735">So if you can just take us through what a
wormhole is, and then we can make the</text><text start="4553.365" dur="7.024">So the wormhole, if you set to solving Einstein’s
equations to figure out, well, what kind of</text><text start="4560.389" dur="6.551">geometries are possible for space time, then
there’s a weird thing that comes out where</text><text start="4566.94" dur="4.2">it’s like you have a black hole in an empty
universe.</text><text start="4571.14" dur="3.7">And then there’s this entirely separate
universe with another black hole in it.</text><text start="4574.85" dur="1.82">So the top and the bottom of this picture.</text><text start="4576.67" dur="1.699">Yeah, so that’s the space.</text><text start="4578.369" dur="3.971">The flat part is the space in one universe,
and then this is like a black hole.</text><text start="4582.34" dur="4.42">But you see it’s connected down to the flat
part, which is like the other universe, and</text><text start="4586.76" dur="2.16">there’s this physical, geometrical connection.</text><text start="4588.92" dur="4.71">So if one person jumped into one black hole,
and the other person jumped into the black</text><text start="4593.63" dur="4.131">hole at the bottom, they could potentially
meet up inside that wormhole, you know, before</text><text start="4597.761" dur="1.338">being annihilated by the black hole.</text><text start="4599.099" dur="2.23">So it’s sort of a tunnel connecting these
two things.</text><text start="4601.329" dur="0.571">That’s right.</text><text start="4601.9" dur="1.04">Are you volunteering?</text><text start="4602.94" dur="2.58">Uh, I’ll pass on that one.</text><text start="4605.52" dur="3.88">Alright, and who--so you may recall I said
remember the year 1935, that was that Einstein</text><text start="4609.4" dur="3.36">Podolsky Rosen, which was that entanglement
that we’ve been discussing.</text><text start="4612.76" dur="7.36">This is also 1935, where it’s Einstein and
Rosen--so again, 2 of the 3 folks involved.</text><text start="4620.12" dur="5.32">And in Einstein’s mind, I think it’s pretty
clear, and correct me if you think otherwise,</text><text start="4625.44" dur="5.62">I don’t think he thought there was any connection
between these two 1935 discoveries.</text><text start="4631.06" dur="6.44">Entanglement on one hand, coming from quantum
physics, wormholes coming from general relativity--completely</text><text start="4637.5" dur="4.63">separate subjects at the time, and some of
the work that you and various of our other</text><text start="4642.13" dur="4.25">colleagues have been pursuing is suggesting
that there’s actually a deep connection</text><text start="4646.38" dur="1.77">between these ideas.</text><text start="4648.15" dur="1.76">It’s truly amazing, so</text><text start="4649.91" dur="4.61">So, I think we’ll sort of step through that
now, if that works for you.</text><text start="4654.52" dur="4.699">So we have a little, you can sort of walk
us through what we’re having here</text><text start="4659.219" dur="1.671">So we’re looking at some kind of universe.</text><text start="4660.89" dur="3.8">There’s a black hole in this universe.</text><text start="4664.69" dur="5.77">And then what’s on the outside is this hologram;
this is the actual mathematical description</text><text start="4670.46" dur="1.98">in our modern way of understanding.</text><text start="4672.44" dur="6.5">So this red around the outside has all of
the information that is telling us what kind</text><text start="4678.94" dur="1.44">of geometry is in there--</text><text start="4680.389" dur="1">So that’s Gerard’s hologram.</text><text start="4681.389" dur="0.571">The information.</text><text start="4681.96" dur="1.64">That’s Gerard’s hologram.</text><text start="4683.6" dur="4.72">On the outside, you’ve got that hologram
in a particular kind of physical configuration.</text><text start="4688.32" dur="4.25">And that’s coding for the fact that there’s
this black hole, and maybe some stars in there</text><text start="4692.57" dur="1.1">in the spacetime.</text><text start="4693.67" dur="0.57">Yeah.</text><text start="4694.24" dur="5.439">And then if we go on and go to the second
black hole in the story.</text><text start="4699.679" dur="1.371">OK, so we show--</text><text start="4701.05" dur="2.53">Alright, now we’ve got two separate black
holes.</text><text start="4703.58" dur="4.329">And basically that’s going to be encoded
by some other information.</text><text start="4707.909" dur="3.031">So you change up the information and now you’ve
got two black holes.</text><text start="4710.94" dur="7.64">Yup, and then if we add to the story a certain
kind of entanglement, say, so...</text><text start="4718.58" dur="6.49">So here what we did was we turned that situation
into one where you have a wormhole connecting</text><text start="4725.07" dur="2.11">behind the two black holes.</text><text start="4727.18" dur="5.66">And the remarkable thing is, in order to do
that in the holographic set, in the holographic</text><text start="4732.849" dur="4.901">description, in the outside description, what
we actually, you know, we have to do something</text><text start="4737.75" dur="1.38">fundamentally quantum mechanical.</text><text start="4739.13" dur="6.009">What we had to do is actually add in a whole
bunch of entanglement between different parts</text><text start="4745.139" dur="1.141">of the hologram.</text><text start="4746.28" dur="2.95">And that was what achieved getting this, this
wormhole.</text><text start="4749.23" dur="5.409">So, just to summarize, because this is a deep
and utterly stunning idea, you’re saying</text><text start="4754.639" dur="8.331">that entanglement in the holographic description,
the red description, is, in the interior description,</text><text start="4762.97" dur="3.02">nothing but a wormhole connecting two black
holes.</text><text start="4765.99" dur="4.99">That’s right, which is, sort of a classical
thing that would have been covered by Einstein’s</text><text start="4770.98" dur="2.68">kind of classical understanding of gravity.</text><text start="4773.66" dur="4.02">It’s just a geometrical connection saying
you could get from here to here, and that</text><text start="4777.69" dur="5.26">property is entirely, according to this--or
according to our current understanding, due</text><text start="4782.95" dur="3.82">to quantum entanglement between different
parts of the hologram.</text><text start="4786.77" dur="5.72">And, moreover, if you find that you can actually
generalize this, that it actually even holds</text><text start="4792.49" dur="1.66">without a black hole in space.</text><text start="4794.15" dur="1.36">So take us from here.</text><text start="4795.51" dur="4.38">Yeah, so I--this was I guess 2009, I was thinking
about that.</text><text start="4799.89" dur="6.309">It seemed crazy, and then one of the things
that you realize if you start reading about</text><text start="4806.2" dur="6.4">entanglement and about just our description
in these theories of just empty space,</text><text start="4812.6" dur="6.3">is that even when you’re describing empty space,
you still have entanglement in the hologram.</text><text start="4818.9" dur="2.76">In the holographic description, there’s
lots of entanglement.</text><text start="4821.66" dur="4.519">And then you sort of ask yourself, well wait,
if that entanglement in the previous story</text><text start="4826.179" dur="5.111">was creating a connection between the two
black holes, could all of this entanglement</text><text start="4831.29" dur="4.429">there, in this picture--could that have something
to do with the fact that the space is sort</text><text start="4835.719" dur="2.411">of connected up into one nice smooth, empty
universe?</text><text start="4838.13" dur="1.279">That space has threads.</text><text start="4839.409" dur="4.482">In some sense, we call it the fabric of space,
is it’s somehow threaded in some manner.</text><text start="4843.9" dur="2.22">Could that be related to this entanglement?</text><text start="4846.12" dur="5.14">And then you were able to mathematically study
that by mathematically cutting the entanglement</text><text start="4851.26" dur="1">lines on the outside.</text><text start="4852.26" dur="1">Right.</text><text start="4853.26" dur="1.74">So it’s what we call a thought experiment.</text><text start="4855" dur="4.75">You just sort of take your math--your description
of this and you say, well what happens if</text><text start="4859.75" dur="1.71">I cut those threads of entanglement.</text><text start="4861.46" dur="1.27">What happens if--?</text><text start="4862.73" dur="2.29">So if we cut some of them—</text><text start="4865.02" dur="4.34">--I take the left half of the hologram and
the right half of the hologram, and I remove</text><text start="4869.36" dur="2.37">the entanglement between those two sides?</text><text start="4871.73" dur="1.3">There’s an effect.</text><text start="4873.03" dur="4.319">You remove entanglement in the hologram, and
then the spacetime starts splitting up, and</text><text start="4877.349" dur="2.591">it, you know, you could actually imagine even
more than this.</text><text start="4879.94" dur="4.36">So you’ve got a ball of clay, and you’re
pulling it apart, and it’s getting further</text><text start="4884.3" dur="6.419">and further apart, and the middle is pinching
off, and so you could keep doing that.</text><text start="4890.719" dur="4.4">You say, well what would happen if I took
away even more entanglement, and took away</text><text start="4895.119" dur="5.641">even more entanglement, and then in this model,
you know, now you’ve got your space and</text><text start="4900.76" dur="2.08">it’s split into four pieces.</text><text start="4902.84" dur="4.08">And I still got a little bit of entanglement,
but I’m going to take that away, and what</text><text start="4906.93" dur="5.169">happens in this description is that the big
nice empty universe that you thought you were</text><text start="4912.099" dur="4.741">describing just splits up into millions of
tiny bits.</text><text start="4916.84" dur="4.399">And once you’ve got no more entanglement
there in this description, you’ve got no</text><text start="4921.24" dur="2.08">more spacetime at all.</text><text start="4923.32" dur="6.06">And so you get to, you know, if this is all
right, you get to this incredibly dramatic</text><text start="4929.38" dur="6.319">conclusion that maybe you’ve just understood
what space actually is, and it’s actually</text><text start="4935.699" dur="6.971">fundamentally quantum mechanical that space
is somehow a manifestation of quantum entanglement</text><text start="4942.67" dur="1.83">in the underlying hologram system.</text><text start="4944.5" dur="6.679">So it’s this beautiful possibility that
we may actually get insight into what holds</text><text start="4951.179" dur="7.441">space itself together, and it may be entanglement
in this holographic description that’s actually</text><text start="4958.62" dur="5.249">threading it all together, which is, you know
I have to say, you know, as a graduate student,</text><text start="4963.869" dur="7.251">I, you know, as a, you have dreams of things
that you might one day gain insight into.</text><text start="4971.12" dur="3.439">Certainly when I was a graduate student, the
idea that we might somehow understand the</text><text start="4974.56" dur="5.7">fundamental structure of space itself, it
was one of those unattainable dreams.</text><text start="4980.26" dur="7.52">And the work that you guys are doing is starting
to reveal a possibility that we may actually get there.</text><text start="4987.78" dur="8.08">So I’m going to personally applaud right
here, because that is just, you know, an absolutely</text><text start="4995.87" dur="4.67">stunning insight which puts together all these
ideas--the ideas of entanglement, the ideas</text><text start="5000.54" dur="2.96">of holography, all put together to gain these
insights.</text><text start="5003.5" dur="6.52">So we’re sort of out there in the depths
of some pretty hefty ideas.</text><text start="5010.03" dur="3.399">We’re just going to spill over for a couple
of minutes, I hope that’s OK with you.</text><text start="5013.429" dur="5.171">Because I just want to sort of pull us back
a little bit to what quantum mechanics can</text><text start="5018.6" dur="7.24">actually do in the world around us that might
actually affect the future of how we do various things.</text><text start="5025.84" dur="3.8">So, Birgitta, you know, you work in the arena
of quantum computing.</text><text start="5029.64" dur="4.36">So, what are the possibilities of actually
harnessing these weird wonderful ideas in</text><text start="5034" dur="4.63">a manner that could actually have an impact
to, say, computing power?</text><text start="5038.63" dur="8.46">Well, over the last 30 years there’s been
a very rapid growth of the field of quantum</text><text start="5047.09" dur="5.549">information, which is really a marriage of
information science and quantum mechanics--and</text><text start="5052.639" dur="2.58">this is still the quantum mechanics from the
1930s, 1940s.</text><text start="5055.219" dur="4.141">You don’t even need relativistic effects
for this.</text><text start="5059.36" dur="7.74">And what we’ve seen is, in the mid-1990’s,
there was a very dramatic publication of an</text><text start="5067.1" dur="6.34">algorithm for doing a quantum--for doing a
calculation factoring large numbers.</text><text start="5073.44" dur="8.38">And this was an algorithm due to Peter Shor,
and this algorithm showed--could be run many,</text><text start="5081.83" dur="5.62">many orders of magnitudes faster if you had
a machine, a computer that was built on the</text><text start="5087.45" dur="5.95">principles of quantum mechanics, using superposition
states, using these wave functions--delocalized,</text><text start="5093.4" dur="5.56">highly delocalized wave functions over many
bits, and principles of entanglement.</text><text start="5098.96" dur="9.48">And then having, however, to maintain the
very delicate quantum nature of the system</text><text start="5108.44" dur="3.1">and not allowing interaction with the environment
to happen.</text><text start="5111.54" dur="5.429">But if you do this, then at the end, after
many procedures--quantum procedures, you would</text><text start="5116.969" dur="5.431">construct a very carefully designed measurement,
and ideally you’d want one measurement at</text><text start="5122.4" dur="6.06">the end and it would be the right measurement
that would give you the answer to your calculation.</text><text start="5128.469" dur="2.031">And are we going to read this?</text><text start="5130.5" dur="6.23">Yes, this was very important, because factoring
large numbers lies at the heart of most of</text><text start="5136.73" dur="5.239">our encryption schemes--the encryption of
your credit cards today, airline tickets,</text><text start="5141.969" dur="2.621">anything that you would think of.</text><text start="5144.59" dur="7.759">And so, from that moment on, the--in a sense
that sort of set the race to build such a</text><text start="5152.349" dur="5.001">quantum computer, and there’s been lots
of advances experimentally then, over the</text><text start="5157.35" dur="1">last 20 years.</text><text start="5158.35" dur="8.039">And we’re now at the point where we have
functioning devices with 9 or 10 quantum bits,</text><text start="5166.389" dur="2.971">the quantum analog of a classical bit.</text><text start="5169.36" dur="7.72">And in the quantum bit, so as we saw those
examples of the spinning electrons.</text><text start="5177.08" dur="6.12">So, classical bit will either be in a state
0 or 1, our digital universe, which we saw</text><text start="5183.2" dur="1.92">in outer space just now.</text><text start="5185.13" dur="7.029">But a quantum bit can be in a superposition--it
can be any arbitrary superposition of 0 and</text><text start="5192.159" dur="8.971">1, which means it will be both 1 or 0, or,
and at the same time, 1 and 0.</text><text start="5201.13" dur="3.13">So it was just carrying this mystery along
with us.</text><text start="5204.26" dur="4.4">And so we now have devices that are functioning
with about 10 of these</text><text start="5208.66" dur="1.499">You say 10?</text><text start="5210.159" dur="1">Ten.</text><text start="5211.16" dur="3.58">Nine actually is the economical number right
now.</text><text start="5214.74" dur="7.66">But people are working furiously now to build
up to about 50, 60, and within a few years</text><text start="5222.409" dur="2.651">we should have somewhere close to 100.</text><text start="5225.06" dur="4.69">And then once we get close to about 100, that’s
a critical number because at that point, one</text><text start="5229.75" dur="6.02">starts to have real technical challenges in
maintaining the quantum nature of the states</text><text start="5235.77" dur="1.69">of these machines.</text><text start="5237.46" dur="6.02">And that brings in these issues of the environment,
decoherence, and also very, very delicate control.</text><text start="5243.48" dur="4.88">And as Gerard mentioned, then you really have
to know many, many many, many variables to</text><text start="5248.36" dur="6.469">really control every one of those variables,
and that’s a really big both physics and</text><text start="5254.829" dur="4.051">engineering problem, which is just starting
to be addressed now.</text><text start="5258.88" dur="6.34">And then after that, I think it’s impossible
to predict how long it would take after that,</text><text start="5265.22" dur="6.98">if at all possible to go up to about 1000
or so, and 1000 is about the number where</text><text start="5272.2" dur="4.52">one would really have a machine which would
do things that couldn’t be computed in the</text><text start="5276.73" dur="2.699">lifetime of a universe--on a classical machine.</text><text start="5279.429" dur="4.711">So that would be the real change for information
processing.</text><text start="5284.14" dur="0.76">Amazing.</text><text start="5284.9" dur="6.92">So we’re just about out of time, but I wanted
to end on bringing this even further down</text><text start="5291.83" dur="5.84">to Earth, because you sort of sort out with
the cosmos, black holes, wormholes, entanglement.</text><text start="5297.67" dur="5.569">There’s a wonderful demonstration in which
these quantum mechanical ideas does something</text><text start="5303.239" dur="3.661">that I find eye-popping no matter how many
times I’ve seen it.</text><text start="5306.9" dur="3.23">Maybe some of you have seen it before--we
have our fingers crossed.</text><text start="5310.13" dur="7.35">Omalon, can you come out one more time with
our--with quantum levitation, if you would,</text><text start="5317.48" dur="6.07">which is a stunning demonstration of again,
some of the strange ways in which quantum</text><text start="5323.55" dur="5.11">mechanics allows the world to work in ways
that, again, a classical intuition would not expect.</text><text start="5328.66" dur="2.34">And Omalon does this freehand.</text><text start="5331.01" dur="3.979">I’m going to stand back and--you want me
to actually touch this?</text><text start="5334.989" dur="1.82">But I’m going to wear a glove.</text><text start="5336.809" dur="5.011">He only wears it to look like he’s being
responsible--I see him do this</text><text start="5341.82" dur="2.02">bare hand all the time.</text><text start="5343.849" dur="2.951">You know, that’s just crazy, alright?</text><text start="5346.8" dur="2.569">That’s like 77 degrees or something?</text><text start="5349.369" dur="2.87">You know, Kelvin, which is cold.</text><text start="5352.24" dur="6.3">OK, so let’s just go right to the disk if
you would, and if you just put that there.</text><text start="5358.54" dur="3.16">And then I’m going to give this a little
bit of a push around.</text><text start="5361.719" dur="1.511">Can you see that, up on the--?</text><text start="5363.23" dur="2.77">Can you get a shot of that?</text><text start="5366" dur="5.14">This is actually just hovering--can I give
it a little bit more of a push?</text><text start="5371.15" dur="4.489">And what’s happening here, if you bring
up the final slide that we have here, it’s</text><text start="5375.639" dur="1.211">called quantum locking.</text><text start="5376.85" dur="5.59">It’s a wonderful application of quantum
ideas that originated with some Israeli physicists</text><text start="5382.44" dur="2.239">who demonstrated this once before.</text><text start="5384.679" dur="4.511">You’ve got magnetic lines that are penetrating
the superconducting disc.</text><text start="5389.19" dur="2.57">It’s cold--that allows it to be a superconductor.</text><text start="5391.76" dur="5.9">And the threads of these magnetic lines are
able to, in some sense, able to pin this object</text><text start="5397.66" dur="0.96">along this track.</text><text start="5398.62" dur="5.18">This track has uniform magnetic field, and
as long as you keep it cold and superconducting,</text><text start="5403.81" dur="1.44">they will hold it in place.</text><text start="5405.25" dur="2.78">Here’s another illustration of these ideas.</text><text start="5408.03" dur="3.15">Look at that, can you get a close-up of that
shot right there?</text><text start="5411.76" dur="2.2">Can you bring that up on the screen?</text><text start="5413.96" dur="0.68">There you go.</text><text start="5414.64" dur="6.26">So you see, that’s just hovering right there,
and there’s nothing in between there.</text><text start="5420.9" dur="4.76">And can we actually--can we flip this over
and show how that goes?</text><text start="5426.28" dur="8.14">Yeah, so we can take this guy...and do you
want...OK.</text><text start="5434.42" dur="1.02">And do you want a glove?</text><text start="5435.44" dur="3.22">No, you just want to do it by hand there.</text><text start="5438.66" dur="1.35">Yeah, OK.</text><text start="5440.01" dur="2.189">More fun that way, he says.</text><text start="5442.2" dur="1.02">OK, yeah.</text><text start="5443.22" dur="1.78">Wow, that’s insane.</text><text start="5445.01" dur="2.84">Now, can you get a shot of that underneath
there?</text><text start="5447.85" dur="11.209">It is now hovering underneath, which is a
fairly stunning and yes, right down to earth</text><text start="5459.06" dur="3.32">demonstration of quantum mechanics.</text><text start="5462.38" dur="2.16">Omalon, thank you.</text><text start="5464.54" dur="1.68">Totally cool.</text><text start="5466.22" dur="1.64">Appreciate that.</text><text start="5467.86" dur="3.94">And I want to thank the entire panel for what
I hope was an interesting journey.</text><text start="5471.9" dur="5.48">David Wallace, Birgitta Whaley, Mark Van Raamsdonk,
and Gerard ‘t Hooft.</text><text start="5477.38" dur="0.82">So thank you very much.</text><text start="5478.2" dur="0.72">Thank you.</text></transcript>