<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" ?><transcript><text start="0" dur="3.52">This is one country I barely have to introduce you to. Let&amp;#39;s just get it over with.</text><text start="3.52" dur="1.34">Sushi, geishas, karate!</text><text start="4.86" dur="1.24">Temples, ramen, anime!</text><text start="6.1" dur="2.04">Sumos, weird stuff, weird cosplay, poison fish,</text><text start="8.14" dur="1.78">and I&amp;#39;m not even gonna ask about that...</text><text start="9.92" dur="1.32">De wa, ikimashou!
では, 行きましょう!</text><text start="13.2" dur="1.94">It&amp;#39;s time to learn Geography</text><text start="15.14" dur="0.84">NOW!</text><text start="15.98" dur="3.12">Hey everybody, I&amp;#39;m your host Barbs.  We have reached the Land of the Rising Sun,</text><text start="19.1" dur="4.56">Asia&amp;#39;s island powerhouse and home to a culture that I&amp;#39;m sure you&amp;#39;ve heard of.  Let&amp;#39;s just jump into it.</text><text start="26.32" dur="2.26">Ah, Japan, you have such a story behind you.</text><text start="28.58" dur="3.16">First of all, Japan is located right off the east coast of the Asian continent</text><text start="31.74" dur="2.08">between the Pacific Ocean and the Sea of Japan,</text><text start="33.82" dur="3.72">stretching all the way from the Sea of Okhotsk in the north with the East China Sea to the south.</text><text start="37.54" dur="4.88">The country is divided into 47 prefectures, each with incredibly beautiful minimalistic style flags.</text><text start="42.42" dur="3.92">The prefectures are divided into four different categories: &amp;quot;ken&amp;quot;, &amp;quot;to&amp;quot;, &amp;quot;fu&amp;quot;, and &amp;quot;do&amp;quot;.</text><text start="46.34" dur="1.22">The first level, &amp;quot;ken&amp;quot;</text><text start="47.56" dur="1.64">(heh heh, &amp;quot;Ken&amp;quot;)</text><text start="49.2" dur="2.82">refers to the 43 plain prefectures.  Then you have &amp;quot;to&amp;quot;,</text><text start="52.04" dur="3.82">which means something like &amp;quot;metropolis&amp;quot;, and this category only applies to Tokyo City.</text><text start="55.86" dur="4.36">&amp;quot;Fu&amp;quot; refers to the urban prefectures, which applies only to the cities of Osaka and Kyoto.</text><text start="60.22" dur="3.5">And finally, &amp;quot;do&amp;quot;, which is a unique category translating to something like &amp;quot;circuit&amp;quot;</text><text start="63.72" dur="2.1">and that applies to all of Hokkaido in the north.</text><text start="65.82" dur="2.94">Speaking of which, Tokyo, Japan&amp;#39;s capital, is the largest city in the world,</text><text start="68.76" dur="4.2">with its greater metropolitan area including Kanto containing about 37 million people.</text><text start="72.96" dur="2.08">That&amp;#39;s more than the entire population of Canada.</text><text start="75.04" dur="5.64">However, Tokyo is kinda like 23 smaller cities all smashed into one, divided into units called wards.</text><text start="80.68" dur="2.66">And the closest thing to a capital one would probably be Chiyoda,</text><text start="83.34" dur="2.42">where the Emperor, Prime Minister, and Supreme Court are located.</text><text start="85.76" dur="4.84">After the Greater Toyko Kanto region, you have the next largest cities Osaka and Nagoya coming in at third.</text><text start="90.6" dur="4.7">Keep in mind, about 90% of people in Japan live in cities, and the vast majority on Honshu and Kyushu</text><text start="95.3" dur="2.3">The busiest airports, of course, being Tokyo&amp;#39;s two twins:</text><text start="97.6" dur="2.04">Haneda, which is actually in Tokyo,</text><text start="99.64" dur="3.3">and Narita International, which is like an hour and a half drive away outside of Tokyo.</text><text start="102.94" dur="2.1">Then you have Osaka&amp;#39;s Kansai International</text><text start="105.04" dur="1.1">&amp;lt;Keith&amp;gt; Heh heh, &amp;quot;KIX&amp;quot;.</text><text start="106.14" dur="1.82">and Fukoka International on Kyushu.</text><text start="107.96" dur="1.12">&amp;lt;Keith&amp;gt; Heh heh, fu-</text><text start="109.08" dur="0.92">Gotta keep it clean, Keith!</text><text start="110" dur="3.54">Speaking of which, Japan is made up of about 6,850 islands,</text><text start="113.54" dur="2.86">but about 97% of the land is made up of four main islands:</text><text start="116.4" dur="1.98">Honshu, Kyushu, Shikoku, and Hokkaido.</text><text start="118.38" dur="2.66">South of the main four, you have the Ryukyu Islands chain</text><text start="121.04" dur="3.52">which extends just south of Kyushu, partially making up Okinawa Prefecture.</text><text start="124.56" dur="3.94">You&amp;#39;ve probably heard of Okinawa – it&amp;#39;s where Uma Thurman got that sword that she used to kill Lucy Liu.</text><text start="128.5" dur="2.6">It&amp;#39;s also where these two isla- *ahem* never mind...</text><text start="131.1" dur="3.54">Nonetheless, Japan can still kind of be separated into ten historical main regions,</text><text start="134.64" dur="1.73">six of which divided amongst Honshu.</text><text start="136.37" dur="3.95">Then you have the interesting less-highlighted Kuril Islands dispute with Russia in the north.</text><text start="140.32" dur="4.46">Basically, Russia administers all of them but Japan claims these two islands closest to Hokkaido:</text><text start="144.78" dur="3.44">Iturup (or Etoro-futo) and Kunashir (or Kunashiri),</text><text start="148.22" dur="2.52">which is only less than ten miles away from Hokkaido.</text><text start="150.74" dur="3">On a clear day, you can even see it from the coast, but it&amp;#39;s like, &amp;quot;Nope! Russia.&amp;quot;</text><text start="153.74" dur="1.24">They even have a statue of Lenin.</text><text start="154.98" dur="2.42">The Russians and Japanese have kind of had a long dispute over this area –</text><text start="157.4" dur="3.2">at one point Japan even tried to take over all of Sakhalin in the 1800&amp;#39;s.</text><text start="160.6" dur="3.66">Then you have the Dokdo/Takeshima island dispute between them and South Korea.</text><text start="164.26" dur="3.5">To this day South Korea has a patrol building built on the island and they fiercely guard it.</text><text start="167.76" dur="2.04">And finally, you have Okinotori-shima,</text><text start="169.8" dur="3.48">which is probably the loneliest place in Japan as a shallow reef in the middle of the ocean.</text><text start="173.28" dur="4.4">It looks like it&amp;#39;s trying so hard to become an island, complete with three helipads and a research station.</text><text start="177.68" dur="5.08">There&amp;#39;s no diplomatic dispute, but rather a dispute within the UN on whether or not it qualifies as &amp;quot;land&amp;quot;</text><text start="182.76" dur="2.04">for an exclusive economic zone in the ocean.</text><text start="184.8" dur="1.94">Whew, okay, all right, that kind of took forever.</text><text start="186.74" dur="1.62">Getting around in Japan is incredibly easy,</text><text start="188.36" dur="3.32">often touted as having the best public transportation system in the world.</text><text start="191.68" dur="3.48">They have highways and trains everywhere, even one that cuts through an office building,</text><text start="195.16" dur="4.64">as well as the Shinkansen bullet train system that can get you to virtually every corner of Honshu and Kyushu</text><text start="199.8" dur="1.6">as well as the bottom tip of Hokkaido.</text><text start="201.4" dur="2">But not Shikoku! If you want to go Shikoku,</text><text start="203.4" dur="3.54">you have to take this slower, local Seto-Ohashi Line across the Seto Bridge.</text><text start="206.94" dur="2.06">Yeah, Shikoku is kind of like the runt of the litter in Japan.</text><text start="209" dur="3.78">Basically, Japan is like one big massive machine constantly running and moving,</text><text start="212.78" dur="3.24">with flashing neon lights, vending machines, and robots, and everything,</text><text start="216.02" dur="3.4">EVERYTHING, even the garbage cans have cartoons, cartoons everywhere!</text><text start="219.42" dur="2.36">Anyway! Some notable places of interest might include:</text><text start="221.78" dur="2.3">Tokyo Skytree, the second tallest building in the world,</text><text start="224.08" dur="0.98">Miyajima Pagoda,</text><text start="225.06" dur="1.96">Matsumoto, Himeji, and Osaka Castles,</text><text start="227.02" dur="2.7">the Fushimi Inari Shrine, the Great Buddha Hall,</text><text start="229.72" dur="2.64">Nakagin Capsule Tower, the vine bridges of Iya Valley,</text><text start="232.36" dur="0.96">the Ramen Museum,</text><text start="233.32" dur="1.98">so many weird-themed restaurants and hot springs,</text><text start="235.3" dur="2.32">the self-mummified monks of sokushinbutsu,</text><text start="237.62" dur="1.46">Henn-na Hotel,</text><text start="239.08" dur="3.12">the Ninja Museum in Iga, Kan-mangafuji Lava Buddhas,</text><text start="242.2" dur="3.78">the restricted-access Ise Grand Shrine, the most significant of all Shinto shrines,</text><text start="245.98" dur="4.36">the Shirakawa-go Traditional Village armed with water cannons to protect itself from fires,</text><text start="250.34" dur="2.56">abandoned theme parks like Greenland and Nara Dreamland,</text><text start="252.9" dur="1.4">Kochia Hill with red cypress,</text><text start="254.3" dur="4.9">and the national treasure, Itsu-Kushima Shrine, featured on numerous pieces of art, films, and even banknotes.</text><text start="259.2" dur="2.4">Now despite the bustling metropolis regions and skyscrapers,</text><text start="261.6" dur="4.06">Japan does an incredible job at maintaining its natural integrity.  Find out how in...</text><text start="268.38" dur="1.88">Now Japan&amp;#39;s land is kind of like a gingerbread house:</text><text start="270.26" dur="2.38">beautiful on the outside, but potentially dangerous on the inside.</text><text start="272.64" dur="5.28">First of all, Japan is a straddle volcanic archipelago located on the most precariously-situated section where</text><text start="277.92" dur="4.8">four major tectonic plates converge: the Pacific, the Philippine, the Eurasian, and the North American Plates.</text><text start="282.72" dur="3.52">Of course, this means that not only is Japan subject to earthquakes but also tsunamis</text><text start="286.24" dur="2.1">(which by the way is a Japanese word – “津波”)</text><text start="288.34" dur="3.22">caused from sub oceanic activities, such as the one recently in Fukushima</text><text start="291.56" dur="2.58">caused by the epicenter in the Japan Trench off the Pacific.</text><text start="294.14" dur="3.86">This also means that Japan is a volcanic area, with numerous volcanoes still active</text><text start="298" dur="4.58">like Aogashima, a volcano within a volcano, and Mt. Aso, the largest volcanic caldera.</text><text start="302.58" dur="2.88">This, in return, also blesses Japan with countless natural hot springs</text><text start="305.46" dur="4.66">which they like to exploit and build bathhouses on called “onsen”, typically indicated with this symbol.</text><text start="310.12" dur="3.58">All this plate activity and volcanoes means that about 70% of Japan is mountainous,</text><text start="313.7" dur="2.52">with the highest peak Mt. Fuji overlooking Tokyo,</text><text start="316.22" dur="3.22">which by the way is still technically an active volcano which erupted about 300 years ago.</text><text start="319.44" dur="3.68">The rift between the Philippine Plate and the Eurasian Plate creates the Japanese Alps</text><text start="323.12" dur="4.18">which bisects the country on Honshu.  This isolated geologic warzone in return, though,</text><text start="327.3" dur="2.96">kinda blesses Japan with an abundance of unique flora and fauna.</text><text start="330.26" dur="3.66">Today, about 70% of Japan is forested, with nice natural water sources</text><text start="333.92" dur="4">like the longest river, the Shinano, and the largest lake, Lake Biwa on Honshu.</text><text start="337.92" dur="1.48">Endemic animals can be found, like</text><text start="339.4" dur="2.76">Japanese hornets, macaque monkeys, tanukis,</text><text start="342.16" dur="2.36">giant salamanders, Bob-tail cats, serow,</text><text start="344.52" dur="1.72">red fox, red crown crane,</text><text start="346.24" dur="4.08">the national dog the shiba inu, the national bird the green pheasant, and the national fish koi.</text><text start="350.32" dur="3.52">Speaking of animals, Japan has quite a few feral animal islands and towns,</text><text start="353.84" dur="3.68">such as Tashirojima the cat island, Okunoshima the rabbit island,</text><text start="357.52" dur="3.3">the town of Miyajima for deer, Miyagi Zao for foxes,</text><text start="360.82" dur="3.14">and of course Jigoku-dani where you can see those monkeys in hot springs.</text><text start="363.96" dur="3.52">With limited space and only about 20% (highly subsidized) arable land,</text><text start="367.48" dur="3.96">Japan has kinda had to think outside the box, so they said, “Hey! Why not go to the sea?”</text><text start="371.44" dur="3.52">Today, Japan is disputably the most advanced aquaculture society on the planet.</text><text start="374.96" dur="2.54">Not only do they have the largest merchant marine fleet in the world,</text><text start="377.5" dur="4.54">but they also harvest everything from shellfish to seaweed in offshore ocean plots and fish farms.</text><text start="382.04" dur="3.64">They love fish – they even have the largest fish market in the world, Tsukiji.</text><text start="385.68" dur="1.88">Speaking of which, we all know about Japanese food –</text><text start="387.56" dur="3.8">I feel like I don’t really have to give you a list of notable dishes like sushi, mochi, or ramen.</text><text start="391.36" dur="5.06">However, Japan is known for making strange flavors of conventional snacks, drinks, and desserts, such as:</text><text start="396.42" dur="2.06">yogurt Pepsi, spaghetti popsicles,</text><text start="398.48" dur="1.52">horse and octopus ice cream,</text><text start="400" dur="1.88">pancake juice, wasp crackers,</text><text start="401.88" dur="2.02">and Kit-Kat has tried pretty much anything under the sun.</text><text start="403.9" dur="1.38">Itadakimasu!
いただきます!
(Let&amp;#39;s eat!)</text><text start="405.28" dur="3.98">Speaking of which, Japan is the third-largest world economy by nominal GDP,</text><text start="409.26" dur="2.4">mostly due to their various technology and automotive industries</text><text start="411.66" dur="3.26">that have swept over the world by storm since the middle of the 20th Century.</text><text start="414.92" dur="4.6">The largest automotive companies include Toyota, Mitsubishi, Honda, Nissan, Mazda, Suzuki, and Subaru.</text><text start="419.52" dur="1.9">As well as tech companies and their subsidiaries like</text><text start="421.42" dur="4.54">Hitachi, Sony, Epson, Canon, Toshiba, Fujitsu, Panasonic, Nikon, and Nintendo.</text><text start="425.96" dur="3.96">This does, however, cause a problem: Japan is classified as a high-throwaway society</text><text start="429.92" dur="2.74">in which lots of resources get unnecessarily used and tossed.</text><text start="432.66" dur="2.2">Like, c&amp;#39;mon Japan! I know you have aesthetic standards</text><text start="434.86" dur="3.18">but seriously, I don’t need one apple in vacuum-sealed plastic wrap!</text><text start="438.06" dur="4.4">Nonetheless, Japan is often seen as one of, if not the, world leader in robotics and tech science,</text><text start="442.46" dur="3.78">receiving more Nobel Prizes in science than any other Asian country. And it’s kind of impressive –</text><text start="446.24" dur="4.44">I mean, with a high population and limited space, Japanese people know how to consolidate and innovate.</text><text start="450.68" dur="1.14">Speaking of Japanese people…</text><text start="454.34" dur="2.98">Now, Japanese people are like, you never know what they’re gonna come up with next.</text><text start="457.32" dur="2.92">You know it’s probably going to be a little weird, but you’re still gonna be a little interested in it.</text><text start="460.24" dur="4.32">First of all, the country has about 127 million people and is the 10th most populous country in the world</text><text start="464.56" dur="2.24">(however, Mexico is getting really close to beating them).</text><text start="466.8" dur="5.04">The country is incredibly homogenous, with over 98% of the populace identifying as ethnically Japanese</text><text start="471.84" dur="4.02">while the remainder is mostly made up of Koreans, Chinese, and very small Caucasian minorities</text><text start="475.86" dur="3.48">of Americans and Europeans, and the indigenous Ryukyu and Ainu peoples.</text><text start="479.34" dur="1.72">They use the Japanese yen as their currency,</text><text start="481.06" dur="2.86">they surprisingly use the Type A American-style plug outlet,</text><text start="483.92" dur="1.82">and they drive on the left side of the road.</text><text start="485.74" dur="3.52">As mentioned like eight seconds ago, Japan has two main indigenous ethnic groups,</text><text start="489.26" dur="1.64">each with their own languages. You have the Ainu,</text><text start="490.9" dur="3.6">which predominantly inhabit Hokkaido and some of the Kuril Islands administered by Russia,</text><text start="494.5" dur="5">known for their rustic, scruffy features, where men grew beards and women used to tattoo their lips and arms.</text><text start="499.5" dur="4.62">Today there are less than 30,000 left, but some estimate that there could be up to 200,000 if you include</text><text start="504.12" dur="4.44">the other Ainu that have assimilated into the rest of Japan and are kind of faintly aware of their own culture.</text><text start="508.56" dur="2.72">Otherwise, you have the Ryukyu people or the “Okinawans”,</text><text start="511.28" dur="4.5">which are kind of like the “Hawaiians” of Japan, known for their own distinct art and traditions and beliefs.</text><text start="515.78" dur="4.22">Now, everybody in the world has had at least a little bit of exposure to some kind of Japanese culture,</text><text start="520" dur="3.6">whether it be samurais, geishas, sumos, kabuki, shamisen music, kimonos,</text><text start="523.6" dur="2.12">and excessively weird products and advertisements</text><text start="525.72" dur="2.54">aimed at using nonconformity as a hook to engage viewers.</text><text start="528.26" dur="3.08">But apart from all that flashy Japan stuff, let’s look at the basics first.</text><text start="531.34" dur="4.62">Japan (no surprise) speaks Japanese which is actually not that hard to learn conversationally,</text><text start="535.96" dur="1.72">but it’s a nightmare when it comes to writing.</text><text start="537.68" dur="3.6">The Japanese language uses three alphabets: hiragana, katakana, and kanji</text><text start="541.28" dur="3.06">(technically four if you include romaji, but that’s kinda like for lazy people).</text><text start="544.34" dur="4.8">The first two, hiragana and katakana, are syllabaries made up of 46 corresponding base characters each.</text><text start="549.14" dur="2.24">That means you have two ways to write each syllable.</text><text start="551.38" dur="3.18">Whereas kanji is basically the list of Chinese characters that they borrowed from China.</text><text start="554.56" dur="2.4">Most students have to learn about 2000-3000 of these.</text><text start="556.96" dur="3.56">That means that Chinese people can kind of get by in Japan just by reading the signs</text><text start="560.52" dur="3.06">as most of the characters have identical meanings, just different pronunciations.</text><text start="563.58" dur="2.98">It’s kind of hard to explain, but the reason why they use three alphabets is because</text><text start="566.56" dur="2.58">each one kind of plays a role for certain words and contexts.</text><text start="569.14" dur="3.74">They don’t use spaces in writing so each alphabet kind of acts as like word dividers,</text><text start="572.88" dur="2.52">and katakana is used for technical and foreign words.</text><text start="575.4" dur="3.68">&amp;lt;Barby 2&amp;gt; Well, why don’t they just fix the problem by using spaces and discard the other two alphabets?</text><text start="579.08" dur="1.66">&amp;lt;Barby&amp;gt; Shut up, that’s why!</text><text start="580.74" dur="4.2">If you didn’t grow up here and actually learn this stuff, you’re either obsessed with Japan or criminally insane.</text><text start="584.94" dur="2.26">Sorry, I’m boring the crap out of you guys with language stuff – anyway!</text><text start="587.2" dur="3.14">Let’s talk about history.  Now I’m sure many of you have seen that video by Bill Wurtz</text><text start="590.34" dur="4.02">(whom I am totally not jealous of considering that he racked up more views and subscribers in two videos</text><text start="594.36" dur="3.74">than I have in all these years of working on this channel), but in the quickest way I can summarize it:</text><text start="598.1" dur="2.8">Yayoi Period, Kofun Period (Yamatos unite Japan),</text><text start="600.9" dur="1.9">Asuka regime (Chinese culture comes in),</text><text start="602.8" dur="1.86">Heian Period (aristocrats take over),</text><text start="604.66" dur="1.92">Kamakura Period (aristocrats lose),</text><text start="606.58" dur="1.8">Shogun Time!, province wars,</text><text start="608.38" dur="2.06">Azuchi-Momoyama Period (things are stable),</text><text start="610.44" dur="2.28">Meiji Restoration (industrialization),</text><text start="612.72" dur="1.78">World War One (Japan’s economy sucks),</text><text start="614.5" dur="2.58">coup d’états and assassination attempts against the Emperor,</text><text start="617.08" dur="3.6">military rule, they try to make an Empire and in World War Two attack Pearl Harbor,</text><text start="620.68" dur="2.46">Nagasaki and Hiroshima, afterwards treaty signed,</text><text start="623.14" dur="3.04">military kind of dismantled and post-war economic miracle. Done!</text><text start="626.18" dur="4.12">Japan definitely sticks out from every country on Earth, and it’s partially because of their belief system.</text><text start="630.3" dur="4.74">Japan is the only country in the world that practices Shintoism, which obviously enough started in Japan.</text><text start="635.04" dur="1.3">If you don’t know anything about Shintoism,</text><text start="636.34" dur="3.7">basically it’s a very ritualistic belief system that reveres a multitude of “kami”,</text><text start="640.04" dur="4.14">which translates to something along the lines of “gods” or “spirits” or “essence”. It’s hard to explain,</text><text start="644.18" dur="3.22">but basically a kami can be manifested in almost anything and everything.</text><text start="647.4" dur="3.38">There are kami for harvests, kami for war, kami for good luck, and so on.</text><text start="650.78" dur="2.98">Today, about 80% of Japanese people practice Shinto to some extent,</text><text start="653.76" dur="3.44">whether it be going to temples or shrines and lighting incense and praying. However, most of them</text><text start="657.2" dur="5.28">will not say that they identify as “Shintoists” since there are no formal rituals to deem yourself a practitioner.</text><text start="662.48" dur="4.94">Otherwise, about 35% might say that they identify as Buddhist and a small 3% are Christians.</text><text start="667.42" dur="5.02">Today there are about 81,000 Shinto shrines and about 85,000 appointed Shinto priests all over the country.</text><text start="672.44" dur="4">Technically, Shintoism is also important because it’s claimed that the Emperor is a direct descendant of</text><text start="676.44" dur="3.88">Amaterasu, the goddess of the sun, which means that the Emperor has the highest authority in Shintoism,</text><text start="680.32" dur="3.46">though today it’s more seen as like a moral tradition and patriotic practice</text><text start="683.78" dur="2.68">rather than believing that the Emperor actually has divine status.</text><text start="686.46" dur="4.04">Oh yeah, and Japan has an Imperial Family with Akihito holding the throne since 1989</text><text start="690.5" dur="2.58">and to this day Japan is the only country with an emperor.</text><text start="693.08" dur="4.42">Some people will say that Shintoism is partially the reason why Japan also has a vibrant, complex industry</text><text start="697.5" dur="4.74">of cartoons and anime, many of which were inspired by Shinto-driven legends and kami. They often rank as</text><text start="702.24" dur="4.66">the top video game producing and playing country in the world – everybody knows Mario, Sonic, and Pikachu.</text><text start="706.9" dur="4.7">In a sense, Japanese people have always admittedly kind of been escapist, creating their own worlds</text><text start="711.6" dur="2.44">and it might be due to their long history of diplomatic isolation.</text><text start="714.04" dur="3.4">In another sense, though, honor and diligence culture is of huge importance;</text><text start="717.44" dur="2.6">having a degree and respectable title is always flaunted.</text><text start="720.04" dur="3.76">The problem, though, is that Japan has the largest aging population in the world in which</text><text start="723.8" dur="6.18">over 26% of the country is 65 or older; in contrast, only about 12.4% are 1 to 14 years old.</text><text start="729.98" dur="4.16">Sociologists have many theories as to why this is, but in addition to a high depression rate,</text><text start="734.14" dur="2.62">there seems to be a lack of sexual interest amongst millennials.</text><text start="736.76" dur="3.78">Especially for men – they even have a word for it: “soushoku-danshi”, or “herbivores”.</text><text start="740.54" dur="4.46">On top of that, Japan has a very strict and conservative approach towards immigration and citizenship. So,</text><text start="745" dur="5.36">ultimately, a smaller generation has to lift the burden of taking care of a population almost ten times their size.</text><text start="750.36" dur="3.5">Many Japanese people are overworked – they even have a word for that: “karoshi”.</text><text start="753.86" dur="1.76">Some wonder how the future will look like.</text><text start="755.62" dur="2.26">&amp;lt;Keith the Elder&amp;gt; Hey son, can you help me cross the street?</text><text start="757.88" dur="5.04">&amp;lt;Barby the Younger&amp;gt; Oh…I would, but you never had a son, so I don’t exist – good luck!</text><text start="762.92" dur="2.78">&amp;lt;Barby&amp;gt; Now you can probably understand why the Japanese are so into building robots.</text><text start="765.7" dur="1.74">There’s so much more we could talk about, like</text><text start="767.44" dur="3.42">how Japan has a strong history in martial arts, folklore, and regional festivals,</text><text start="770.86" dur="2.14">but this video is already getting long and I have to cut it down.</text><text start="773" dur="2.4">Some notable people of Japanese descent might include people like:</text><text start="775.4" dur="3.44">Emperor Hirohito, Fukuzawa Yukichi, Honda Tadakatsu,</text><text start="778.84" dur="2.94">Kukai, Maeda Toshiie, Tokugawa Ieyasu,</text><text start="781.78" dur="3.12">Murasaki Shikibu, Saigo Takamori, Akira Kurosawa,</text><text start="784.9" dur="2.88">Hayao Miyazaki, Soichiro Honda, Miyoshi Umeki,</text><text start="787.78" dur="2.76">Hibari Misora, Rinko Kikuchi, Osamu Dazai,</text><text start="790.56" dur="2.82">Kei Nishikori, Ayumi Hamasaki, Takeshi Kitano,</text><text start="793.38" dur="2.92">Masayoshi Son, Akria Toriyama, Sadako Ogata,</text><text start="796.3" dur="2.68">Taiho Koki, Masako Katsura, Ichiro Suzuki,</text><text start="798.98" dur="2.3">Hanae Mori, Ken Watanabe, Downtown Duo,</text><text start="801.28" dur="1.88">Keisuke Honda, and Shinji Kagawa.</text><text start="803.16" dur="2.52">Now due to their history, Japan has always been like a “lone wolf”,</text><text start="805.68" dur="4.54">but over time they learned how to open up and let&amp;#39;s find out how in the last segment, the…</text><text start="813.34" dur="2.12">So Japan is a pretty big player on the world stage.</text><text start="815.46" dur="4.66">As a member of the G20, G8, IMF, WHO, UN, EAS, Interpol,</text><text start="820.12" dur="2.9">and, like, 400 other acronyms, they know diplomacy pretty well.</text><text start="823.02" dur="2.92">They get along with Brazil, Peru, and the Philippines pretty well,</text><text start="825.94" dur="2.64">as each country contains many Japanese communities. In addition,</text><text start="828.58" dur="4.76">lots of people from these countries either visit or work in Japan. Peru even had a Japanese president.</text><text start="833.34" dur="4.76">As mentioned in the France episode, Japan kind of sees France as the epitome of European exoticism.</text><text start="838.1" dur="3.14">After English, French is one of the most highly-desired languages to learn</text><text start="841.24" dur="3.02">(although good luck, considering how every French word ends in a consonant).</text><text start="844.26" dur="4.46">The Pacific island nations of Palau, Kiribati, and the Marshall Islands still hold close ties, even though</text><text start="848.72" dur="2.66">Japan kind of occupied them during the first half of the 20th Century.</text><text start="851.38" dur="3.34">Japanese people love visiting and provide business and revenue for these countries.</text><text start="854.72" dur="2.66">Their biggest frenemies are South Korea and China.</text><text start="857.38" dur="4.62">These three are like the Asian trifecta, dominating most of the business and affairs in the East.</text><text start="862" dur="2.88">Despite Japan having invaded and occupying these two for decades –</text><text start="864.88" dur="2.92">my own grandmother was actually raised in Japanese-occupied Korea</text><text start="867.8" dur="1.82">and to this day she still speaks fluent Japanese –</text><text start="869.62" dur="3.96">they’ve mostly moved on, plus the whole North Korea thing kind of makes South Korea and Japan closer.</text><text start="873.58" dur="2.54">The youth of today love piggybacking off of each other’s’ cultures:</text><text start="876.12" dur="3.5">Koreans and Japanese admit it, they can’t get enough of Japanese anime and video games,</text><text start="879.62" dur="1.86">whereas the Japanese are obsessed with K-pop.</text><text start="881.48" dur="3.34">And, you know, they kinda got kanji and Buddhism from China, so, uh, there’s that.</text><text start="884.82" dur="2.26">In terms of their best friends, however, interestingly enough,</text><text start="887.08" dur="3.5">most of the Japanese people I’ve talked to have said the USA and Taiwan.</text><text start="890.58" dur="3.68">Even though they don’t officially recognize Taiwan as a sovereign state on paper,</text><text start="894.26" dur="3.28">they totally act like they do and stand with them on pretty much any diplomatic measure.</text><text start="897.54" dur="4.42">Taiwan was actually the longest-lasting occupied area under Japanese rule during the Empire years,</text><text start="901.96" dur="1.64">and they have since then still kept close.</text><text start="903.6" dur="3.2">Even though the pains of World War Two will never be forgotten, it’s funny because</text><text start="906.82" dur="4.34">almost immediately after that the US and Japan started skipping down the street hand-in-hand.</text><text start="911.16" dur="2.72">The US kind of felt like a duty to make reparations since</text><text start="913.88" dur="3.58">there were already communities of Japanese-Americans, especially in Hawaii and California –</text><text start="917.46" dur="2.14">my hometown Los Angeles has a Little Tokyo –</text><text start="919.6" dur="4.74">so they invested tons of money in Japan after the war and in the 50’s Japan started booming in every industry.</text><text start="924.34" dur="4.96">Culture cues were adopted on both sides: McDonald’s opened up in Tokyo, 7-Eleven opened up in the US,</text><text start="929.3" dur="3.64">they love burgers and Chris Evans, and we have nerds living in their mom’s basements</text><text start="932.94" dur="3.78">rewatching every season of Naruto Shippuden with ill-fitting cosplay outfits.</text><text start="936.72" dur="3.84">In conclusion, the Land of the Rising Sun has always kind of figured that the best way for them to</text><text start="940.56" dur="4.44">open up to the world was to create their own worlds with wild imaginations driven by technology,</text><text start="945" dur="3.8">yet still beautifully preserving the ancient vibrant values of their ancestors.</text><text start="948.8" dur="1.58">Oh and by the way, this episode was brought to you by</text><text start="950.38" dur="2.4">Bob Saget’s Bearsharktopus Coffee Shoes!</text><text start="952.78" dur="2.62">Watashi wa KOOHII to kutsu ga hoshii
私はコーヒーと靴がほしい
(I want coffee and shoes)</text><text start="955.4" dur="2.46">Let&amp;#39;s super harassment sandwich!</text><text start="957.86" dur="2.2">Stay tuned: Jordan is coming up next.</text></transcript>